kilometres but
kilometres but
the
the
I am
I am
able.
able.
He is also the secretary-general of our headquarters. Let's welcome him first.
也是我們院本部的秘書長 我們先歡迎他
Also present here are academician Li Zhenhui and several people from our hospital.
還有在座有李貞暉院士 還有我們院內的幾位
Distinguished Research Fellows and Research Fellows
特聘研究員 還有研究同仁
and ladies and gentlemen and students
以及各位女士 各位先生 各位同學
Welcome to our Academia Sinica
歡迎大家來參加我們中央研究院
Feast of Knowledge in February
2月份的知識饗宴
The Feast of Knowledge at Academia Sinica is a popular science speech
中央研究院的知識饗宴是一個科普的演講
I hope that every outstanding researcher of Academia Sinica
希望把中央研究院 每一位傑出的研究員
The results of these studies have been shown in an in-depth manner
所做的這些研究成果 以深入顯出的方式
to introduce to the public
來跟大眾做介紹
Today we are delighted to be able to invite
今天我們很高興能夠邀請到
Special Researcher Wu Jinglie is also our Secretary-General Wu
吳經烈特畢研究員 也是我們的吳秘書長
Come and talk to us all about it
來跟我們大家做相關的演講
Let me briefly introduce Secretary-General Wu
我現在簡單的介紹一下吳秘書長
Secretary-General Wu is from the Longhua Department of National Taiwan University
吳秘書長他是在台大龍化系
After getting a bachelor's and a master's
得到了學士跟碩士以後
at Arkansas University School of Medicine
在美國阿肯社大學醫學院的
Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology Receives Ph.D.
生化幾分子生物學系得到博士學位
that after receiving a Ph.D. in 1975
那在1975年得到博士學位以後
He returned to the Institute of Zoology, Academia Sinica
他就回到中央研究院動物所
which is now the cell
也就是現在的細胞
Institute for Individual Biology
與個體生物學研究所
research work
擔任研究的工作
Later served as Deputy Director
後來也擔任了副所長所長
So for 38 years he has been working on
所以38年來他不斷致力於
Basic research and applied research of aquatic biotechnology
水產生物技術的基礎研究跟應用研究
You may have seen glowfish on the seals
大家可能看到海豹上有螢光魚
Everyone is curious, who invented the fluorescent fish
大家都很好奇,螢光魚是誰發明的
We can ask the secretary general to talk to us later
我們等一下就可以請秘書長來跟我們講
The process of developing this fluorescent fish
這個螢光魚研發的過程
quite wonderful
相當的精彩
actually in this
實際上在這個
Secretary-General Wu's research
吳秘書長的研究上
is a prospective fish study of Taiwan
是對臺灣這些前瞻的魚類研究
There are also aquatic features
還有水產的特色
Do this fish biochemistry
進行這個魚類生化
Fields of Study
跟分生的研究領域
In today's information, you can see
在今天的資料上大家可以看得到
Many innovative research results
創新研究成果很多
Including the development of the muscles and liver of this zebrafish
包括這個斑馬魚的肌肉跟肝臟的發展
and the use of zebrafish as an animal model
還有利用斑馬魚作為動物模式
to study the human Python and hepatitis virus
去研究人類的畢形跟細型肝炎的病毒
How to cause intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma
怎麼樣引起肝內的膽管癌
This is a very innovative research
這是一個很創新的研究
what about the other
那另外呢
Innovative research includes
創新的研究包括了
Mechanism and Prevention of Fish Virus Infection
魚類病毒感染的雕王機制跟防治
There is also the sculpture control of muscle growth
還有肌肉成長的雕控
Research on regulation and balance
調控還有抗衡的研究
and viewing
還有觀賞
Fluorescent ornamental fish
螢光觀賞魚
There is also a turning point due to poor control of the fish
還有轉機因魚的不運控制
If you bought a glowfish today
如果你今天買了一隻螢光魚
These fluorescent fish can also give birth to the next generation
這些螢光魚還可以生下一代
This glowfish probably won't sell for a lot of money
這個螢光魚大概不會賣很多錢
If this fluorescent fish can't give birth to the next generation
如果這個螢光魚不能生下一代
Then you wait until this fluorescent fish dies
那你等到這一隻螢光魚死的時候
I have to buy another one, right?
還要再去買另外一條對不對
So the unlicensed technology is very important
所以那個不運證的技術就很重要
Let your industry of this fluorescent fish
讓你的這個螢光魚的產業
able to thrive
能夠蓬勃發展
So how do you make the fish unlucky?
那怎麼樣讓魚不運呢
This is a very deep technology
這個是一個很高深的技術
We can also find out later
等下我們也可以來了解
Then its research results are published in the main
那它的研究成果發表在主要的
A total of 201 academic journals
學術期刊一共有201篇
He also holds 6 US patents
他也擁有美國專利有6件
Taiwan has 9 patents
臺灣專利有9件
And there are already 8 pieces counted
而且其中計轉的已經有8件
And he insisted on being in the world
並且他也硬要在世界上
These famous monographs
很著名的這一些專書
There are a total of 20 articles written in this chapter
寫這個專章的文章一共有20件
This Wu Distinguished Researcher is also
這吳特聘研究員也是
Our Secretary Wu
我們的吳秘書長
As I said just now, he served as the deputy director and the director
他剛才我講過擔任過副所長跟所長
that for the whole animal
那對於這個整個動物所的
research and infrastructure
研究還有基礎建設
made a great contribution
有很大的貢獻
In addition, he also served
那另外他也擔任過
The very important position of our central researcher is called the executive secretary of the Academic Advisory Association
我們中央研究員很重要的職務叫做學術諮詢總會的執行秘書
And the director of the dean's office
還有院長辦公室的主任跟
It is
現在是
secretary general
秘書長
that help promote the academic development of the College
那協助推動本院的學術發展
have important responsibilities
具有重要的責任
In addition to the service in this hospital
那除了在本院的服務以外
Our Secretary-General Wu for his
我們吳秘書長他對於
Nationwide agribiotech push
全國的農業生技的推動
also play an important role
也扮演很重要的角色
So he promoted the adoption of agricultural biotechnology by the painting department
所以他推動了畫部會的農業生技採用
Industry Promotion Program
產業推動方案
in this plan
在這個方案當中
Hope to promote Taiwan's agricultural biotechnology industry-university cooperation
希望能夠帶動臺灣的農業生技的產學合作
and industrial guidance
還有產業化的輔導
And how to authenticate and sanpinhua
以及如何認證跟三品化
These things are quite important
這些東西都是相當的重要
So Secretary-General Wu in 2013
所以吳秘書長在2013年
Awarded this Agricultural Biotechnology Contribution Award
獲頒這個農業生技貢獻獎
It is obvious that Secretary-General Wu's promotion of Taiwan's entire agriculture
顯見吳秘書長對臺灣整個農業的推動
play a very important role
扮演很重要的角色
In addition to playing a very important role in domestic agricultural biotechnology
他除了在國內的農業生技扮演很重要的角色
Promotion of international academic research
對於國際上的學術研究的推動
also play many important roles
也扮演很多重要的角色
including his past experience as a member of the International Committee for Scientific and Technical Information
包括他曾經擔任國際科學及技術資料委員會
叫MOON
叫HOLDATA
and the International Council for Science
還有國際科學理事會
ICSU
ICSU
and the International Union of Biological Sciences
還有國際生物科學聯合會
Member of the Executive Committee of IUBS
IUBS的執行委員會擔任委員
So it is a very important contribution
所以是有相當重要的貢獻
More importantly, Taiwan International Sea was established in 2012
更重要的在2012年成立臺灣國際海域
Society of Deep Object Technology
深物技術學會
And he is the chairman
而且他擔任理事長
So no secretary can say
所以無秘書長可以說
All the way to Taiwan's agricultural biotechnology
一路走來對台灣的農業生計
Especially aquatic biotechnology
特別是水產的生物科技
made a great contribution
有很大的貢獻
Of course someone with such a good performance
那當然有這麼好的傑出表現的人
Must have won many academic awards
一定獲得很多的學術獎項
including ten outstanding young people
就包括十大傑出青年
Of course when he was young
當然是他年輕的時候
And this National Science Council Distinguished Research Award
還有這一個國科會傑出研究獎
And Hongjindui's
還有弘金堆的
Distinguished Honor Award
傑出榮譽獎
National Science Council Special Investigator
國科會的特別研究人員
and Distinguished Special Investigators
還有傑出特別研究人員
So many awards
所以獎項無數
So if you want to hang
所以如果要掛起來的話
The medals on my body are endless
身上的勳章是掛不完的
what about today
那今天呢
very happy
很高興
Wu special researcher will come to tell us
吳特殊研究員會來跟我們講
deep object technology
深物技術
and the sustainable development of deep marine resources
與海洋深物資源的永續發展
Then wait a minute and everyone can listen to his speech
那等一下大家可以聽聽他的演講
just know
就知道
his contribution to this
他在這一方面的貢獻
and very important marine
而且很重要的海洋的
this deep resource
這個深物資源
It is very important for our human health
對於我們人類健康是很重要的
so
所以
Today we hope that after listening to his speech,
今天我們希望大家聆聽了他的演講以後
be able to return home with a full load
能夠滿載而歸
And after a big meal
而且有很豐盛的一餐以後
have a rewarding experience other than
有滿載而歸以外
Gain better knowledge
在知識上也能夠有更好的收穫
So now let's give this kind of applause
所以現在就讓我們以這類的掌聲
Come welcome Master Wu Yun
來歡迎吳運士長
applause
掌聲
First of all, thank you Dean Chongwu for this introduction
首先謝謝崇烏院長的這個介紹
Award-winning introduction
過獎的介紹
Distinguished guests, Mrs. Li Yan, directors
各位貴賓 李燕氏 各位所長
Mr. Lee
各位李氏先生
Dear colleagues, fellow students, hello everyone
各位同仁 各位同學 大家好
then i am ordered today
那我今天奉命
Mr. Chen Wuyun said this, right?
這個陳吳運長說這個是不是呢
knowledge in Chinese
在這中文就言的知識
Miss this popular science speech
想念的這個科普的演講
Can introduce my field of research
能夠介紹我研究的領域
Then let everyone learn from this scientific research
那麼來讓大家來從這個科學的研究
Then it can be implemented on the popularization of this knowledge
那麼能夠落實在這個知識的普及上面
then i today
那我今天
speak today
今天講
It is one hole combining two
就是一孔結合兩個
One is the sustainable development of marine biological resources
一個是海洋生物資源的永續發展
If applied to the most important fields of biotechnology in the 21st century
如果應用21世紀的最重要的生物技術領域
Let the resources of our planet's oceans
讓我們地球的海洋的資源
i don't stress
我不強調
Usually we speak from various human-centered subjective viewpoints
通常我們在各種以人類為主的主觀的觀點來講
perpetual use
都常常永續利用
use seems too subjective
利用好像太主觀
Then I think sustainable development is a harmony
那我覺得永續發展的話是一個和諧
and a concept of coexistence
而且共存的一個概念
Let our planet's resources
讓我們地球的資源
especially raw resources
尤其是生資源
sustainable development
可以持續的來發展
then we all know
那麼我們各位都了解
I'll watch this first
我先看這個
Sorry
Sorry
what about our earth
我們地球呢
actually a water polo
事實上是一個水球
right
對不對
That is to say, the earth
也就是說地球呢
largest area
最大的面積
It is also this water that covers
也是這個水覆蓋著
So we say Earth's
所以我們說地球的
It's unique, it's in the universe
是unique 是宇宙裡面
human knowledge
到現在以人類的知識
Haven't found an environment like ours
還沒有找到跟我們地球一樣的環境
with plenty of water and air and sunlight
具有充分的水 還有空氣 還有陽光
Enough to conceive for the creature to evolve
足以孕育 讓這個生物演化出來
So the creatures on our planet Earth
所以我們地球地球上的生物
Without water, it can be said that there is no living thing
沒有水可以說就是沒有生物
aerobic bacteria without oxygen
沒有氧氣可以有氧氧性的細菌
but without this oxygen
但是沒有這個氧氣
It is absolutely impossible for any living things to exist without water.
沒有水的話絕對不可能有任何的生物存在
so we can all understand
所以我們都可以了解
The water or ocean is very important
這個水或是海洋是非常重要的
So what I'm telling you today is that the ocean is
所以我今天跟各位講就是海洋是包括
Not only sea water is fresh water, but it is also made of acquatic resources
不只海水是淡水就是以acquatic的資源來做了
What we know about
我們了解的探討
So the outline of mindfulness that I am going to tell you today
那麼我今天跟各位講的念容大綱
probably under this area
大概有這個區下
One is that we use Taiwan to exchange our eyes for the world
一個就是我們以台灣來換眼國際
Check out this comparison between Taiwan and the rest of the world
看看這個台灣跟國際的比較
Our situation in the development of marine biotechnology
我們在海洋生物技術的發展的這個情況
Compare this with ours
跟我們的這個這個比較
so what
所以呢
Because I participated in the report of the deputy dean just now
因為我參與剛剛副院長的報告呢
I'm the one who's involved in our country's
就是我參與這個我們國家的
agricultural biotechnology
農業生物技術的這個
industry development
產業的發展
So what about our development strategy?
所以呢對我們的發展策略呢
so let you know
那麼讓各位了解
So our biotech industry
所以我們的生物技術產業
How to develop in this area
在這一塊怎麼樣去發展
What about the third one?
第三個呢是
in my lab
我實驗室裡面呢
did some research work
做了一些研究工作
Some important points mentioned by the vice president just now
剛剛副院長有提到的一些重點呢
and then explain it very clearly
然後做很開要的來來說明
Then as a strength
那麼作為一個實力呢
Let everyone know what is marine biotechnology
讓大家了解說什麼是海洋生物技術
or biotechnology in aquaculture
或是水產養殖的生物技術
Then the fourth item is of course
那麼第四項當然要講
What about the application of marine biotechnology?
這個海洋生物技術的應用呢
Innovate with the industry
跟產業創新
this is very important
這個非常重要
If Taiwan does not have no innovation
台灣如果沒有沒有創新
Drive the development of the industry
帶動產業的發展
I think Taiwan may be so competitive
我想台灣可能這種競爭力呢
There is no way to do this in the international
是沒有辦法在國際的這個
We can take the lead in this industry platform
這個產業的平台裡面我們可以得到領先
So industry innovation
所以產業的創新
If research results from academia can be translated
如果從學術界的研究成果可以轉換過來
I also want to make some introductions on this part
這一塊我也希望做一些介紹
Then the fifth item is that we now talk about food safety
那麼第五項就是我們大家現在說講食品安全
Very important
非常重要
So our food safety regulations in Taiwan
所以我們台灣的食品安全規範
After all, it is in line with international norms, especially in terms of water length
到底跟國際的規範尤其在水長方面
where are we the same
我們相同的地方在哪裡
where is our weakness
我們不足的地方在哪裡
The shortcomings are what we must pursue
不足的地方就是我們一定要追求的
Otherwise, there is no way for our industry to be internationalized.
要不然我們的產業是沒有辦法國際化的
Then the last thing is to put my personal experience in the field of marine biotechnology
那麼最後就是把我個人的在這個海洋生技領域
Promotion through the Society
透過學會的推廣
Then let's drive the development of Taiwan's technology
那麼來帶動台灣的這個科技的這個發展
And finally the future
那最後是未來展望
let's look at the first
那我們看看第一個
This comparison of the development of international and Taiwan marine biotechnology
國際與台灣海洋生技是發展的這個比較
That just mentioned that the earth is a water globe
那剛好提到地球是一個水球
Then the total surface of the earth is 360 million square kilometers
那麼地球的總表面計是3.6億平方公里
71%
有71%
ocean cover
海洋覆蓋
So of course there's this blunt bluntness that's bred in it.
所以當然這裡面孕育了這個烘烏的直言
Calculated by the amount of protein that naturally exists on the earth
以地球自然存在的蛋白質的量來算的話
In fact, 90% of the animal protein on the earth is
地球上其實90%的動物性的蛋白質
living things in the water
是在水裡面的生物的
So it can be seen that the ocean is very, very important to us
所以可見這海洋對我們是非常非常重要
no ocean can be said to be our side
沒有海洋可以說是我們這邊
there is no way to survive forever
就沒有辦法永續的存活
So develop this marine industry
所以因此發展這個海洋的產業
Not only do we get food
我們不但獲取食物
We can also acquire new medicines
我們還可以獲取得到新的醫藥品
Energy and Permeable Chemicals
能源跟透用化學品
So often in the discussion of various technologies
所以常常在各種的科技的討論
Everyone thinks that Ossisky humans need to develop further
都認為奧西斯基人類要再實際發展
Shou County because of the land
因為土地的壽縣
The ocean is where we can still play
海洋是我們仍然可以去發揮
important area
重要的一塊領域
So is the technological revolution that thinks blue
所以是認為藍色的科技革命
This includes the development of technology
這是包括科技的發展
Application with industry
跟產業的運用
The biggest problem facing us as human beings
我們人類面臨最大問題
now everyone knows
現在目前大家知道
Earth's population is still increasing
地球人口還在增加
Climate change causes, for example, the warming of the earth
氣候變遷造成比如地球的暖化
There is also pollution that causes the environment in which we live
還有汙染造成我們存活的環境
getting worse
越來越惡化
The third is the circulation of human diseases
第三個就是人類的這種疾病的流通
Or aging is a very important issue for everyone
或者是老齡化都是大家很重要的問題
Let's see in 200 years
我們看看在200年的時候
Earth's population has exceeded 6 billion
地球人口已經超過60億
In 2013 and 2011, it has exceeded 7.1 billion
2013年2011年就已經超過71億
this is amazing
這個非常驚人
Nearly 900 million people in ten years
十年中間就將近了差不多9億的人口
It is estimated that the earth's population will reach 9 billion by 2050
預估2050年地球人口會到90億
will still go up
之後還是會往上漲
Then here comes the problem
那現在問題就來了
The expandable area of ​​the earth is actually shrinking in a straight line
地球的可更面積其實是直線縮小
population has been increasing
人口一直增加
And it can be seen that this trend emerges
而且可以看到這個趨勢出現
Still pretty much this Stip
還是相當的這個Stip
Although the population of our Taiwan is growing world ranking shop
雖然我們台灣的人口是增長世界排名店舖
But for Obole, the whole world is still...
但是Obole來講全世界還是...
A child is born with only one mouth
生下一個小孩就一張嘴巴
For a mouth to eat you have to have enough food for them to eat
一張嘴巴要吃你就要有足夠的食物來讓他們吃
So the problem facing our planet
所以我們地球面臨的問題
If the biological resources of the ocean are combined with technology
如果從海洋的生物資源加上科技
The development of biotechnology can solve the
生物科技的發展才能夠解決
not too long before 2050
到2050年不太久
only 37 years
只有37年的時間而已
do a lot more
再做很多都
Still on this earth for more than 37 years
37年多都還在這個地球上面
what are we going to eat
我們要吃什麼
this is a worldwide problem
這個是一個世界性的問題
It's not just Taiwan's problem
不是只有台灣的問題而已
So because we in Taiwan are very lucky
所以因為我們台灣非常幸運
We not only have mountains and land
我們不但有高山有土地
It's more important for us to have the ocean, right?
我們更重要有海洋對不對
So in the far sea countries of the ocean
所以在海洋的遠海國家
Well, besides us, Taiwan can develop agriculture
那麼除了我們台灣可以發展農業
and industrial biotechnology
還有工業的生物技術
Medicine Beyond Biotechnology
醫藥的生物科技以外
Marine Biotechnology We Are Not a Landlocked Country
海洋生物技術我們不是內陸國家
If we were Mongolia today
我們如果今天是蒙古
Then we didn't show off our power in this area.
那這一塊我們就沒有發威空
Maybe we need to develop the wood industry, right?
這可能我們要發展木業對不對
But our Taiwan ocean
但是我們台灣這個海洋
The investment in marine biological technology has a great impact on our eleven system-based entertainment
海洋生技術的投入對我們十一制度型娛樂
Such resources can be used continuously
這樣的資源就可以永續來利用
So for us Taiwan is an ocean country
所以對我們台灣一個海洋的國家
is very important
就顯得特別的非常的重要
So in our government and academic research
所以在我們的這個政府跟學術界的研究裡面
First we can see that
首先我們就可以看出來就是
In this marine life technology that can develop
在這個能夠發展這個海洋生技術
Promote innovative industrial development with the basic biological blood position foundation
用基礎的生物血位基礎推動創新的產業發展
academic and industry
學術跟產業
The need for the concept of truth is particularly prominent in Taiwan at present.
真相這個概念這個需求對台灣目前特別顯
Because not only the industry needs to develop
因為不但產業要發展
create our economy
創造我們的經濟活路
It also creates job opportunities
同時也創造就業機會
Then let our industry be on the international stage
那麼讓我們的產業可以在國際上面
Can compete with others
可以跟人家一平高下
At the same time our continued use of the marine environment
同時我們對海洋環境的持續的利用
that is very important
那是非常重要的
Whether we can destroy our marine environment
我們不論可以破壞我們的海洋環境
or access to these resources
或者是可以獲取這些資源
Well, because we are doing basic research
那麼因為我們是做基礎研究
Therefore, the field of flower houses should start from the basics
所以花宅領域要從基礎開始
So at the base we except molecular biology
所以在基礎我們除了分子生物學
the flower field reproductive biological genetic
這個花域 生殖 生物 遺傳
Genomics Gene transfer
基因體學 基因轉職
then wait
那麼等等之外
The study of disease is very important and immune
對病的研究非常重要 還免疫
Because the control of this disease is
因為這個疾病的控制對
not only important to people
不但對人重要
It is also necessary for these creatures
對這些生物它也是必要的
from here we can
那我們從這邊可以
not only get this food
不但獲取這個食物
At the same time we can get biological active substances
同時我們可以得到生物的活性物質
so in the ocean
所以在海洋裡面
For example, we are famous in Taiwan
比如說我們台灣很有名的
We get collagen from Wu Guoyu Yilin Tablets
從吳國瑜遺林片我們得到膠原蛋白
then from some early years
那麼從一些早年
Recently, flower houses in Taiwan usually get this crane halide
最近台灣的花宅通常得到這個鶴藻糖膠
Can be used as an adjunct to chemotherapy for this cancer
可以作為這個癌症化療的輔助
very effective product
非常有功效的一個產品
Therefore, the active substances of marine organisms
所以海洋的生物的活性物質
There is a lot of room for development
是有很大的領域空間可以去發展
then the marine environment
那麼對海洋環境的
Sustain applications that include energy
維持包括能源的應用
including this removal of contamination
包括污染的這個去除
biotechnology for the marine environment
那麼海洋環境的生物技術
is very important
是顯得非常的重要
so what
所以呢
This extends to the industry
這這樣子就延伸到產業
What about Taiwan?
那台灣呢
This technology of production and breeding in the past is very good
過去生產養殖的這個技術是很好
So we keep introducing new technology
所以我們不斷導入新的科技呢
Let Taiwan's production and breeding technology
讓台灣的生產養殖科技呢
able to continue to use
能夠持續來運用
Personally, I will dig deeper in this area.
這這一塊我個人琢磷會比較深一點
That pair of marine naturals blossoming into medicine
那對海洋天然物開花為藥物
Flowering into new biomaterials
開花為新的生物材料
What about materials that blossom into energy?
開花為能源的材料等等呢
These are quite potential
這些都是相當的有潛力
And finally, the protection of the environment
那最後呢對環境的保護
What about resource management?
跟資源的管理呢
it's all about this
都是對於這個這個
In terms of application, it has considerable potential.
應用方面呢是相當的有潛力的
so let's see
所以我們就看看
The countries of the world these from Asia
那世界各國這些從亞洲
all the way to this Europe
一直到這個這個歐洲呢
What about the countries of the world?
世界各國呢
It's in the research field of marine biotechnology
它在海洋生物科技的研究領域呢
it does some tidying up
它做了一些整理
Discovery, such as Asian countries
發現呢比如亞洲國家
It says that 80% of aquaculture production is in the Asian region
它說是水產養殖的產量80%在亞洲地區
Therefore, countries in the Asian region include Taiwan
所以亞洲地區的國家包括台灣以外
China, India, South Korea, Japan, Southeast Asia and other countries
中國、印度、韓國、日本、東南亞等國家
Aquaculture, marine biotechnology
對水產養殖、海洋生技術
In particular, Taiwan attaches special importance to
尤其台灣是特別的重視
Various resources including living organisms and other biofuels
包括還有其他生物燃料的生物的各種資源
Just mentioned medicine, food, feed, peanuts, etc.
剛剛提到的醫藥、食品、飼料、花生等等
are doing
都在做
The same goes for other countries
那其他國家也大同小異
But the resources of marine organisms are different
但是海洋生物的資源品種不一樣
Fish, Shellfish, Shrimp, Microorganisms
魚類、貝類、蝦類、微生物
algae are different
藻類都不一樣
so spendable features
所以可以花費的特色
find new discoveries
找到新的發現
Of course, each from the biological conditions
當然就是各自從生物條件裡面
to find our specialties
去找到我們的特色
We are all very familiar with Taiwan
台灣我們大家非常熟悉
You may not know the number
大家可能數目就是比較不了解
The world has 440,000 kilometers of coastline
全世界海岸線有44萬公里
Taiwan's coastline is 1,600 kilometers long
台灣的海岸線長度有1600公里
About the whole world of the earth
大概占了地球的全世界
One-fourth of the total length of the coastline
海岸線總長四百分之一
That's not bad, isn't it?
那也不錯啦 對不對
We think Taiwan is small
我們認為說台灣很小
Actually not small
其實不小喔
because of this
因為這個這個
Our coastline is still in the world
我們的海岸線還是在世界上
can still be listed as our length
還是可以列為我們的長度
The second important thing is our Taiwan
那第二個重要就是我們台灣呢
Where's this black grass from the south?
從南方來的這個黑草呢
has two tributaries
有兩個支流
The mainstream is from the east coast of the Pacific
那主流是從太平洋東岸
It's from Hualien and Taitung.
就是花蓮、台東這邊上來
Yilan keeps going up
宜蘭一直上去
What about other tributaries?
那麼另外從支流呢
from the Taiwan Strait
從台灣海峽上去
So what about this luck?
所以這個運益呢
we are very rich
我們非常豐富的
the resources of the ocean
這個這個這個海洋的資源
then let this this
那麼讓這個這個
The conditions of our marine ecology are particularly good
我們的這個海洋生態的條件特別好
For example, the earth is better than the earth
比如是地球比用地球上
Types of fish probably
魚類的品種大概
24,000 to 5,000 species
兩萬四千到五千種
already recorded
已經有記錄的
There are more than 2,300 kinds of fish in Taiwan
台灣的魚類就有兩千三百多種
recorded
有記錄的
that is one tenth
也就是十分之一
Therefore, although Taiwan is small
所以在台灣雖然是小
But biological resources are very rich
但是生物資源呢非常豐富
What's more, we have three hundred kinds of Sanwu
更何況我們有三百種的三五啊
The doubling of the 2,500 species
那兩千五百種的這個一倍加列
So
那麼
The next series has 340 kinds
下系列有340幾種
So this kind of style research is
所以這樣的風物質研就是
we can play
我們可以去發揮
to make scientific discoveries
去做科學發現
basis for future applications
跟將來應用的基礎
Then Taiwan's production and breeding
那麼台灣的生產養殖
Well, they are actually talking
那麼其實他們都是講
From Zheng Shenggong to Taiwan
從鄭生公到台灣的時候
Started to develop private equity farming in Tainan
就開始在台南發展私募養殖
Isn't that very out of the ordinary?
那是不是非常出況
But also Taiwan's production and breeding
但是也台灣對生產養殖
Our ancestors were already very familiar with
我們的祖先就是已經非常熟悉
can only use the resources of the ocean
只能利用海洋的資源
Cultivate such delicious fish
培養這麼好吃的魚類
So from 1661 to 1962
所以從1661年到1962年
you see so long
你看這麼長的時間
Then it is a pastoral farming
那麼是一個放牧式的養殖
More out of the ordinary farming and herding fish, etc.
比較出況的養殖牧魚等等
Then we start
那麼之後我們就開始
Successful technology with development above
有發展的成功科技上面
Raising grass lotus carp and grass shrimp
養草蓮魚 草蝦
Artificial link of mullet
烏魚的人工環節
This technology was introduced in the 660s of the Republic of China
這技術在民國660年代
5060s established technology
5060年代就建立了技術
Then we started to combine technologies
那技術我們就開始有結合
corporate farming
企業化的養殖
This is Taiwan from 1970 to 1979
這是台灣70年到79年
It was the glorious era from the 1960s to the 1970s
就是60年到70年代很風光的時代
then based on this
那麼由這個基礎
So we know Manyu and Caoxia
那麼所以我們知道漫語跟草夏
Both call Taiwan the Kingdom of Manyu
都稱為台灣是漫語王國
or the Grass Summer Kingdom
或是草夏王國
Grass summer is hardly cultivated now
現在草夏是幾乎沒有養殖
It's the king carved the king
是王雕了王
But this is of course a sick question
但是這個當然有病的問題
then i mean
那我意思就是說
I remember when I just returned home
我記得我剛回國的時候
Manyu farming is officially the most prosperous time
漫語的養殖是正式最興旺的時候
At that time Taiwan
那時候台灣
At that time, when Manyu was exported, one kilogram was
漫語外銷那時候一公斤是
about 10 dollars
差不多10塊美金
At that time, one to four was 10 yuan
那時候一比四10塊
dollar one dollar
美元一塊美金
At that time, we exported from Taiwan every year
那時候我們台灣每年外銷
Probably reached 1 billion US dollars
大概有到達10億美金
It is Guangman language export has always been
就是光漫語外銷一向
In just one year, the NT$40 billion at that time
就一年就當時的400億的新台幣
So go to Manyu City
所以到漫語市那邊
those rambunctious bosses
那些漫語的老闆
Taipei City is still driving this era of empty talk
台北市還開這個當空話車的時代
I have already done a lot of driving Benz and VNW
已經去做很多都是開Benz跟VNW了
what about later
那後來呢
Grass summer cultivated
草夏養殖過
When going to the south to go to the shrimp pond, there are also double B cars driving
到南部去養蝦池那邊也都是雙B的車子在開
So that's all the glory days
所以那就是榮景都過去了
We can't always remember the glory
我們不能夠一直緬懷榮景
Disappeared due to illness
因為病的關係就已經消失掉了
So we have sick problems
所以我們有病的問題
There is the problem of groundwater subsidence, etc.
有地下水下陷的問題等等
So we are already afraid to talk about the so-called kingdom
所以我們就已經是不敢再講說所謂的王國
But we are in this recession
但是我們在這個衰退的時候
The government still invests a lot of funds to introduce biotechnology
政府還是投入了很多的經費導入生物技術
Hope Taiwan can continue to lead
希望台灣能夠持續領先
In fact our technologies
事實上我們這些技術
Especially in mainland China or Southeast Asia, India, etc.
尤其在中國大陸或是東南亞、印度等等
I very much hope that these new biotechnologies in Taiwan that produce and raise bats
都很希望台灣的這些生產養蝠的新的生物科技
You can go to these countries to develop this industry
可以到他們的這些國家裡去發展這個產業
Here's the Science Development for Our Congressional Bloggers
這是我們國會博主的科學發展
the analysis they did
他們所做的分析
The resources we just talked about in the repo
我們在回購的剛剛講到生物的資源
The resources of the ocean cannot be sustainable
海洋的資源它沒有辦法永續
Because humans overfill it, right?
因為人類濫補啊 對不對
Pollution, wait
污染啊等等
Then I will give two examples
然後我就舉兩個例子
One is from this our
一個就是從這個我們的
We love to eat tuna Sashimi
我們喜歡吃鮪魚Sashimi
But everyone understands
但是大家了解啊
When is the highest peak in Taiwan?
台灣最高峰的時候呢
Where is this Sashimi?
這個Sashimi呢
not tuna
不是 鮪魚呢
Can catch 10,000 tails a year
一年可以捕獲一萬尾
about fourteen years ago
大概是十四年前
Now catch only five hundred and five tails
現在捕獲只有五百零五尾
This resource is
這個資源是
This decline is very fast
這個衰退的非常快
This is our responsibility
這個是我們人 我們有責任的
So how about technology
那麼怎麼樣科技
So in fact in some countries
所以事實上在一些國家
in australia mexico
在澳洲 墨西哥
They have developed the only farming industry
他們已經有發展唯一的養殖產業
We do not have such an environmental management in Taiwan
我們台灣還沒有這樣子的環境經營
the only meaning is to say
唯一意思就是說呢
When resources are scarce
資源匱儉的時候呢
Then this can only be developed by breeding
那麼這個只好用養殖的方式來發展
The second one is that the mullet roe will grow this year
第二個 今年過年烏魚子長
the price is very
價格非常
So because we used to peak at
那麼因為我們過去高峰在
At this time of the American League East?
在這個美聯 東制的時候呢
I remember when I was a kid
我記得在小時候呢
I'm getting better. Wow, everyone is so happy.
我物益起來了 哇大家好高興
Because every year Taiwan catches
因為每年台灣抓的
So that fishery technology is not very good
所以那漁業技術還不是很好
Every year, one million tails are caught, and the material benefits of two million tails
每年都抓百萬尾 兩百萬尾的物益
There's value in it, right?
那裡面可以取物益值 對不對
Now the annual catch may be 200,000 to 300,000
那現在一年抓到的可能是二三十萬
So like this year, there are almost 300,000 tails
所以像今年也是差不多三十十萬尾
So the material benefit value becomes very noble
那麼所以物益值就變成非常的高貴
very expensive good
非常的貴 好
Then it's resource-hungry
那麼這是資源匱乏的
But Taiwan also has a place to overcome
但是台灣也有一個克服的地方
It is the material benefit that Taiwan can raise a whole foot
就是台灣可以養全尺的物益
Raised for two to three years
養了兩年到三年
The benefit value can be raised to almost a sum
物益值可以養到差不多一筆
Can be raised to 8292
可以養到八兩九兩
Quality is hardly grasped naturally
Quality幾乎不是天然抓的
So this technology can still overcome
所以這個科技還是可以克服
this scarcity of resources
資源的這個匱乏
So this technology in Taiwan
所以台灣的這個科技
That is, aquaculture technology
就是說水產養殖科技
Molecular Biology
接由分子生物學
What's more, the development of this algae biotechnology
還有呢發展這個藻烈生物技
This is our Taiwan
這是我們台灣的
more important
比較重視的
Can provide many of our needs
可以提供我們很多的需求
So
那麼
Humans just mentioned that humans will rely on
人類剛提到人類會依靠
this
這個
With the product as a source of food
隨產品作為食物的來源
So
那麼
The adsorbed ones are usually better than the road ones
吸附的通常是比路上的
regular chicken
一般吃的雞肉
This pork is more expensive
這個豬肉還要貴
and
而且
also many times more expensive
也要貴很多倍
So
那麼
economic development
經濟發展
The consumption of adsorption will definitely increase
吸附的消耗一定會增加
so this
所以這個
A statistic from the world's FAO
全世界FAO的一個統計
It was 2007
就是2007年
Everyone in the world eats it a year
全世界每個人一年吃掉
16.7 kg of fish
16.7公斤的魚
So
那麼
18.6 kg in 2010
2010年就18.6公斤
About 26 kg to 28 kg in Taiwan
台灣大概26公斤到28公斤左右
We in Taiwan still eat fish
我們台灣還是吃魚
eat more
吃比較多
so
所以
This consumption is increased
這個消耗量它是增加的
but
但是
fish eaten here
這裡面吃的魚
some fish
有的魚撈的
Some are from aquatic products
有的是水產羊豉的
There are two sources
這裡面兩個來源
then you can tell
那麼你可以看得出來
The blue piece of the egg
這蛋的藍色這一塊
yes
是
worldwide
全世界
Doubts about compensation
補撈的疑惑
so far probably because of resource management
到目前大概都因為資源的管理
probably it doesn't grow much
大概它都不太成長
A little bit can probably replenish the amount
一點大概能夠補貨的量
About 90 million metric tons
大概是9000萬公噸左右
Doubtful
疑撈的
Then it's this piece
那生然是這一塊呢
In the past, the amount of breeding was very small
過去呢養殖量非常少
You can tell it started almost 20 years ago
你可以看出來差不多從20年前開始
This growth rate is rapidly increasing
這成長率是快速增加
Can you see this number?
可以看出來這一個數目字呢
8% annual growth rate
每年有8%的成長速度
2012 is last year
2012年就是去年
Farmed production is 66 million metric tons
養殖的產量有6600萬公噸
70,000 metric tons this year
今年就是7萬公噸
So by 20 years maybe 20 years
所以到20年大概20年
The yield of farming will be higher than that of old fish
養殖的產量會高過於漁老的
So this industry is developing
所以這個產業它是發展的
demand is rapidly increasing
需求是快速增加的
so it's a trend
所以這是一個趨勢
Just mentioned it is until 2018
剛提到就是到2018年
Then farming will exceed the amount of catch
那麼養殖就會超過補撈的量
Well so these only depend on so although farming to provide
那麼所以這些只有依靠所以雖然養殖來提供
Then let's see where Taiwan ranks
那我們就看看台灣的位階在哪裡
Taiwan although we have a large fleet catching fish
台灣雖然我們有很大的船隊在抓尾魚
still catch this squid
還抓這個魷魚
But we have limited fish species to catch
但是我們有限定魚種在抓
So even though we are like this
那所以雖然我們這樣呢
Taiwan catches fish all over the world
我們台灣全世界補撈魚呢
Up to 15 million tons in China
最多是中國1500萬噸
Taiwan is 850,000 metric tons
台灣是85萬公噸
That fights against the one percent of the world
那戰世界這些百分之一
In fact, we don't catch much
其實我們補撈量不多
But what we catch is more expensive fish
但是我們抓的是比較高價的魚
This is how much we make up
這是我們補撈的量
What about breeding?
那麼養殖呢
What about us in Taiwan?
那麼我們台灣呢
Because we are limited to our area
因為我們授限於我們的面積
but what about our output
但是我們的產量呢
About 310,000 metric tons
大概31萬公噸
Then China is more than 47 million metric tons
那麼中國是4700多萬公噸
So this amount is very large
所以這量是非常大
Then Taiwan and world production is 0.10%
那台灣戰世界產量是0.10%
So but we use small things to make big things
所以但是我們是以小博大
We have good industrial technology
我們有好的產業技術
Then let's replace our yield
那麼來代我們的產量化
So our quantity is definitely small
所以我們的以量絕對是小
But the level of technology we have to present
但是科技的水準我們要呈現
So
那麼
So look at the world
所以以世界來看
Not only Taiwan
不只用台灣
From the perspective of the world
以世界來看
This is the maximum yield
這是最大的產量
because oysters
因為牡蠣代口
It is only 12 million tons
它1200萬噸才很多
but in terms of fish
但是以魚的話
The first one is mostly because of China
第一個最多是因為中國
keep a lot of carp
養很多鯉魚
3.5 million tons a year
一年就是350萬噸
The second most is this shrimp
第二多的是這個蝦類
3.8 million tons
要380萬噸
The third is no abalone
第三是無鮑魚
is 2.85 million tons
是285萬噸
Salmon is 1.7 million tons
鮭魚是170萬噸
probably can see
大概可以看得出來
When your fish species are all million tons
當你魚種都是百萬噸級的
output to develop
產量來發展
so so we this
那麼所以我們這個
exist
在
In terms of the world or Taiwan
世界或是台灣來講
Then it can be seen from the above analysis that
那麼剛從上面的分析可以看出來
The importance of nutrients
鮮養質重要性
so
所以
this
這個
Because fresh nutrients
因為鮮養質
output can
產量可以
with your amount
跟你的量
So
那麼
More importantly, in animal feed
更重要就是在動物的飼料裡面
We often say that cost is feed conversion power
我們有常常講成本就是飼料轉換力
It is Fit Conversion Ration, FCR
就是Fit Conversion Ration, FCR
As for fish farming, the feed is very good now
養魚呢,現在養的很好的飼料呢
Some 1.2 to 1.5 kg of feed
有的1.2到1.5公斤的飼料
1 kg of fish will grow out
會長出1公斤的魚肉出來
But what about the kilogram statistics
但是,公斤的統計呢
this, this
這個,這個
What about this, this grass-rock sports animal?
這個,這個草石運動物呢
About 8 kg of feed
大概要8公斤的飼料
Is it better to add 7, it is 2
是不是是加7是比較好,是2
But the conversion efficiency of fish is more
但是魚的轉換效率更加
Then, more importantly
那麼,更重要的就是
For the identification of farmed diseases
對於養殖的病的identification
Disease detection, what about medical technology?
病的檢測,它醫療技術呢
It's quite mature now
現在其實蠻成熟
What about research in this area in Taiwan?
那台灣在這方面研究呢
A considerable amount of research has also been invested in
也投入相當多的研究成果
Well, for the health mentioned just now
那麼,對於剛剛提到健康
and food safety
以及食品安全呢
That aquatic product is very important
那水產品非常重要
In particular, we mentioned that apart from talking about high-quality protein
尤其,我們提到除了說優質的蛋白質以外呢
This, this fish meat still has very elegant
這個,這個魚肉裡面還有很很有風物的
collection
Omega3
then this is
那麼這個是
There is no way to provide the meat we are talking about
我們講的肉類是沒有辦法提供的
So in terms of health needs
所以對健康的需求來講
it is very important
它是非常重要
so i mention one more number
所以我再提一個數字
just mentioned numbers
剛才提到數字
is our seed balance
就是我們的種餘額量
then 1.2 million metric tons
那麼有120萬公噸
Then there are about 300,000 to 450,000 metric tons in breeding
那養殖有大概30、45萬公噸
About 28%
大概占28%左右
What about the output value?
那產值呢
Taiwan's remaining output value is about 100 billion
台灣的餘額產值大概1000億了
Breeding about 38 billion
養殖大概380億
That output value accounted for 35.7%
那產值占35.7%
Indicates the value of the rest of the breeding
表示說養殖的餘的價值
Slightly higher than Yu Lao's calm value
稍微高於餘老的平靜的價值
We understand Taiwan's international
我們了解台灣在國際上面
We farm
我們隨場養殖
some of our status
我們的一些地位
After this pros and cons
跟這個優缺點以後
Let's look at Taiwan in
我們看看台灣在
Sorry
Sorry
Strategies for development in this area of ​​marine biotechnology in Taiwan
在台灣在這個海洋生技術領域發展的策略
Of course we usually talk about strategy
那當然我們通常講策略
usually do a
通常就會做一個
Analysis of some pros and cons
一些優劣式的分析
digital analysis
數碼的分析
Just now I mentioned that Taiwan has these characteristics
剛才講台灣有這些特色
We are often proud to say
我們常常自豪就是說
Taiwan's farming technology
台灣的養殖技術
and feed technology
還有飼料的技術
The technology of the viewing instrument is carefully selected
觀賞儀的技術都詳意選球
This is not a problem
這是沒有問題的
Second we have a lot of talent
第二個我們有很多人才
The third one is that we have very close cooperation in industry, relations and academia
第三個我們產關學界的合作非常密切
our chance is
我們的機會就是
We are able to develop multifaceted outcomes
我們能夠發展多面向的成果
including industrial applications
包括工業的應用
Applications in the medical industry
醫療產業的應用
Ours is structured
我們的這個有建構
Asia-Pacific's Aquatic Total Second Center for this condition
亞太的水產總秒中心的這個條件
Because regardless of mainland China
因為不管中國大陸那邊也要
or Southeast Asian countries
或是東南亞國家
They all went to Taiwan to ask for talent
他們都到台灣要人才
Need technology
要技術
This is indeed where we are going to develop
這個確實是我們是到那邊去發展
But we also have some points
但是我們也有一些點
for example
就是譬如說
Industry relocation
產業外移
Technology integration is not good enough
技術整合不夠好
insufficient funds
資金不夠
Natural resources are scarce
天然資源比較缺乏
We've been trying to find ways to overcome him recently.
最近我們都想辦法來給他克服
The third is research strength
第三個就是研究實力
I want to report to you about my research strength
研究實力我要跟各位報告
is our laboratory
就是我們實驗室
I went to such a long time for a study
我去這麼長的一個研究時間
in manor circle
在莊園圈
Because I just said as the Generalissimo
因為我剛剛像總委員長說的
There is also some burden on aquatic technology
對水產生技方面也負擔了一些
We do part of the planning and promotion work
我們部分做規劃跟推動的工作
So our laboratory is of course still based on
所以我們的實驗室當然還是以
molecular biology
分子生物為主
economic research
經濟的研究為主
to study important aquatic farmed animals
來研究重要的水產的養殖的動物
animal with pattern
跟模式的動物
then research
那麼就是研究
Then we address important topics
那麼我們對重要的課題
boneless fish
跟魚種包括無骨魚
Grouper
石斑魚
and zebrafish
還有斑馬魚
ornamental fish etc.
觀賞魚等等
These are the objects of our research
這些是我們研究的對象
Then the subject will grow against it
那麼課題會針對它成長
Because of raising this animal
因為在養這個飼養動物
growing
成長的
Speed ​​is an important source of determining its income
快慢是決定它的收益很重要的來源
You grow fast, it has a yield and payback will be quicker
你長得快,它有一個收益回收會快
Second, as environmental changes and disease risks are reduced
第二個,成當環境變化跟疾病的風險也會減少
So growing is, usually breeding
所以成長是,通常是養殖
No matter from breeding to feed flowering is the most important part
不管從育種到飼料開花是最重要的一環
The second is disease monitoring and disease prevention
第二個是疾病的監控跟疾病的預防
Often breeding inside now the world statistics
常常養殖裡面現在全世界統計
About 40% of losses due to disease deaths
因為疾病死亡損失大概佔了40%
So the disease can sometimes even reach 100%
所以疾病的有時候甚至會達到百分之百
Therefore, disease prevention is very important
所以疾病的預防是顯得非常重要
Ornamental instrument
這邊特別提到觀賞儀
Taiwan is a viewing instrument and is currently on the top of the international
台灣是觀賞儀算是目前在國際上面
still the most competitive country
還是最有競爭力的國家
Competing with us is mainly Singapore
跟我們競爭主要是新加坡
Singapore used Southeast Asia for its Forte acquisition
新加坡它是用東南亞做它的復地收購來
it transfer center
它轉應中心
We in Taiwan really have four to five hundred kinds of ornamental instruments
我們台灣是真正有四五百種的觀賞儀
in Taiwan
在台灣一種
That is exported from Taiwan
那由台灣外銷出去
So we are actually more advanced than Singapore and more advanced in the industry.
所以我們是其實比新加坡又有在產業比較前端
Then we have our advantage
那我們是有佔有我們的優勢的
Then the question of guilt
那麼涵害的問題
Then I just mentioned that there are some unsuitable technologies to be imported
那麼剛提到有一些不應的技術要導入
Then let this industry develop
那麼來讓這個產業可以來發展
The following are the topics
那下面就是介紹這些課題
let everyone know
讓大家了解
Therefore, our research topic will be selected from this excellent tracing
所以我們研究課題就會從這個優良的走描的選拔
Especially for those who have no national interest
尤其是針對無國益方面
The second one is that we build this technology of gene transfer
第二個我們建立這個基因轉存的這個技術一類
Then the third is the growth path
那麼第三個是成長速徑
Low temperature resistance is also useful for industrial development
低溫的抵抗還有觀賞於產業的開發
Especially fluorescent viewing technology
尤其是螢光觀賞於技術
Our team does a pretty good job of working with the industry
我們的團隊跟業界合作做得相當不錯
That's because it's a gene rotator
那因為是基因轉子
So we need a suitable platform to build
所以我們需要有不應的平台來建立
It is more important that we do a good job in technical research
那更重要我們要把技術研究做好
So let's look at this excellent
那麼我們看看這個優良
This is what everyone needs to know
這個是大家要了解的就是
any of us
我們任何的
You need to produce economically for this animal and plant
這個動植物你要做經濟的生產
Then you have to go through preseeding
那你要經過預種
What about pre-planting?
那預種呢
Then you have to inherit the genetic method
那你就要遺傳遺種的方式
that is, selected
也就是選拔出來
genetic traits
遺傳的特性
Then your characteristic, for example, is to grow.
那你的特性比如說要生長啦
Wait, what about the different features you want to choose?
等等這些不同的特性你要選的話呢
Then you have to go through its quantification
那你要經過它這個數量化
Then look at its gene, this
然後呢看它的這個基因的這個
its this trade
它的這個trade
What about the mark of this gene?
這個基因的這個這個標記呢
can identify it
可以把它identify出來
as pre-seed
作為預種
For example, if you grow up, you want to
比如說你你成長是你要
fast growing
生產成長快的
large fish
體型大的魚
the fish
的魚
no fish
無過魚
Then you pick the front end
那你就挑最前端的
That can grow up to 800g fish
那可以長到800g的魚
streaming fish
流位的種魚
then continue breeding
那繼續再配種
so you can
所以呢你就可以
You can pre-seed
預種呢你可以往
grow fast
成長快速
big fish
體型大的魚呢
Then you can produce it
那麼你就可以把它生產出來
What about the other inherited traits?
那其他的這個遺傳的這個特性呢
We can also pass this
我們也可以透過這樣的
this this this genetic this
這個這個這個遺傳的這個
mark to filter
標記來篩選
that due to the development of molecular biology
那由於分子生物的發展
This property of genes can be established
基因的這個特性可以建立起來
So now combine
所以現在結合了
molecular genetic marker of DNA
DNA的分子的遺傳標記
Generations of genetic variants can be shortened
可以縮短遺傳異種的世代
That is, the time can be reduced
也就是時間可以減少
So in the past, for example
那麼所以過去比如說
It takes 8 years for you to inherit the inheritance
你遺傳遺傳要花8年的時間
Inherited markers combined with DNA
配合上DNA的遺傳的標記
Can shorten the time by about half
可以縮短一半的時間大概
So accelerated genetics
所以加速遺傳遺種
Allows the industry to develop
可以讓產業可以發展
So it is the auxiliary relic that becomes the mark
所以就是變成標記的輔助遺種
there is a marker
有一個marker
In the past there was no marker
過去是沒有marker
then inside
那麼inside
The old man who defends me is advanced enough
保衛我的老人還夠高級
That's before you grow up
那現在就是還沒養到大以前
I have a marker that says
我就有marker說
With this marker, it will grow bigger
有這個marker就是會長得大
So for this marker, you first use the firmness of DNA
所以這個marker你先用DNA的堅定
Then you can leave this
然後你就可以把這個遺留下來
Huanli Next Generation
就環利下一代
So by doing this you can also reduce
所以透過這樣也可以減少
This total time
這個這個預總的時間
so we
所以我們
We cooperate with aquatic leads
我們跟水產線索合作
it has the same time
它有同樣的時間
These two body types can be different
這個兩個體型就可以差了
nearly 50%
將近50%
So we use
所以我們用
For example, using traditional DNA
比如說用傳統的DNA的這個
This marking of the RF LOP
RF LOP的這個標記
it can be seen
就可以看出來
this grows fast
這個長得快的
use this two different
用這個兩個不同的
Limiting beauty of DNA to cut
DNA的限制美去切割
The pattern that these two become
它這兩個變成的pattern
Same as this original
跟這個一般原來的
it's different from total
與總它就不一樣
So we went after these two
所以我們就追著這兩個
This cut of HINF 1 and RASA 1
HINF 1跟RASA 1的這個切割的
fragments of DNA
DNA的片段
Then you can have a marker
那你就可以有一個標記
This is already considered traditional
這是已經算是傳統的
There is a way
有方法
Then use a markup like this
那麼用這樣的標記
then you can also choose to say
那你也可以選說
Why choose no national language
為什麼無國語要選
All-male stateless
全雄性的無國語
Because there is no national language
因為無國語
Everyone says it's good
大家說很好養
wonderful period more exciting
精彩期精彩多
but there is
但是那是有
XY's
XY的
male
雄性的
words with XX
跟XX的詞
What about when only sexual fish are together?
只性的魚在一起的時候呢
Wu Guoyu is almost four months old
無國瑜他差不多四個月
He copulates as soon as he is sexually mature
他就性成熟就交配了
So if the fish is not big, he will only be the next generation
所以魚不大他就還只下一代
That's a big one
那養得很大呢
need to provide all
就需要全部都供的
All the energy provided by him is
全部供的他能量就
Won't you go after your girlfriend?
不會去刷追女朋友嘛
so he grows big
所以他就長得很大
so so say look at us
那麼所以說你看我們
the quarter before the event
活動前面的那個四分之一
There are so many Wu Guoyu
無國瑜好多
Then they will all come after girlfriends
那麼他們都會追女朋友來
live with him
跟他住在同一個
In this round tide
圓圓的這個潮裡面
you have a chance to see
你們有機會去看一看
Extremely fun
非常好玩
that now means
那現在就是說
How big does Wu Guoyu have to be?
這無國瑜要養得多大
Wu Guoyu can be raised to more than three kilograms
無國瑜可以養到三公斤以上
Three kilograms
三公斤
So I'm going to Jiaoxi this weekend
那麼我這個周末到礁西呢
there is a restaurant
有一家餐廳呢
because tv said
因為電視說
Wu Guoyu can become a restaurant's family
無國瑜可以變成餐廳的家養
and very expensive
而且非常貴
One customer needs to go alone
一客要一個人去
Of course not eating Wu Guoyu directly
當然不直接吃無國瑜
He still eats class ten
他還吃十班啊
Nine holes and so on
九孔等等
But Wu Guoyu is playing the main role
但是無國瑜是在主打的
he just wants
他就是要
Fish over 2.5kg
2.5公斤以上的魚
He said that such a big fish is good
他說這麼大的魚肉才好
will be strong and delicious
會結實好吃
really good
果然不錯
too small fish
太小魚
Turtle meat is soft
烏龜的肉比較軟
After arriving there, it will be full of this angular diameter
到那邊以後就滿有這個角徑
And the fish is quite sweet
而且魚肉相當的甜
i mean
我意思就是說
super male turtle fish
超雄性的烏龜魚
That's also sifting with potato marcos
那也是用土豆馬可來篩選
So of course we've also been using the new Marco lately
所以當然我們最近也用新的馬可
is called microRNA
就是叫做microRNA
fragments of microRNA
就是微RNA的片段
as a new marker for growth
作為生長的新的標記
So we analyze
所以我們透過這樣分析
also get the new tag
也得到新的標記
can be used as molecular marker screening
可以作為分子的標記篩選
related to growth
跟成長有關的
the second one
那第二個
Because of the first rotor technique
因為第一轉子技式
like everyone said a lot
像大家講的很多
How to use it in fish
魚類裡面怎麼去運用
Let us introduce to you
我們這邊跟各位介紹一下
this is very beautiful
這個是很漂亮的
Because Taiwan can be said to be the only one in the world
因為台灣可以說獨步全球
the fastest
走得最快的
It is through the precise technology of fish
就是透過魚類精準的科技
Trained from small chairs to medium chairs
培養出來從小型椅到中型椅
even to large chairs
甚至到大型椅
in various colors
有各種不同顏色的
green, red, yellow
綠色、紅色、黃色的
we can become a beautiful
我們可以變成一個美麗
And very vivid new colorful world of fish
而且很生動的魚類的新的彩色世界
So goldfish eggs are not just for ornamental fish
所以金魚卵子它不只做觀賞魚
We can also use it
我們也可以用它
If you grow faster
你如果加速生長
disease resistance, resistance
抗病、抗力進
Increase feed conversion
增加飼料的轉換率
basic research
可以在基礎研究
can also be promoted
也可以來推動
Increase nutritional value
增加營養價值
genome research, etc.
基因體的研究等等
All kinds of fish can play different roles
各種魚都可以扮演不同的
role of research purpose
研究目的角色
Understand the technology of the new transfer
懂得新轉職的技術
we know in simple terms
我們知道簡單來講
It is the color body of our plastid
就是我們一個質體的彩體
you cut through the first known
你經過先知名的切割
you can put the gene you want
你可以把你要的基因
Put it in this plastid
放到這個質體裡面去
into this plastid of such a recombinant BNA
成這樣一個重組的BNA的這個質體
So, for example, we put in the genes of foreign aid
那麼比如說我們放進去外援的基因
For example, the production base will grow fast
比如說生產基數它會長得快
Or this epitope that we put in Star Qiannian
或是我們放進去明星乾年的這個表面抗原
Then there will be vaccines and so on in the future.
那將來要做疫苗等等
Make medical protein
做醫藥蛋白
What about after putting it in?
那放進去以後呢
What about this plastid?
我們把這個質體呢
Beat into the egg box of the fish's fertilized eggs
打到魚的受精卵的卵盒裡面去
So what happens after the gene for foreign aid enters?
那麼這個打外援的基因打進去以後呢
The gene of this foreign aid
這個外援的基因
For example production base then it will cut into this fish
比如說生產基數那麼它會砍入這個魚的
For example, this case is salmon
比如說這個Case是鮭魚
Then it goes inside this dyed bottom
那麼它的這個染色底裡面去
So because of the production base
那麼因為生產基數呢
Imported this salmon, it grows faster
都導入了這鮭魚它就長得比較快速
In fact it's already licensed to do this in the U.S.
事實上在美國已經合準它可以做這個
This genetically modified fish should be transferred commercially
商業化應轉的這個基因轉值的魚
What about the conversion technology?
那轉值的技術呢
I'm just going to talk to you guys very quickly.
我就簡單跟各位很快講過去一下
earliest start
最最最早開始
Started with this microinjection method
開始是用這個顯微注射方法
The straight DNA just mentioned
那把剛剛講的直體的DNA
you load in very thin capillaries
你裝載在很細的毛細管
Then its capillary is very stretched 0.1-0.5
那它毛細管是很牽0.1-0.5
microscopic glass needle for microphone
麥克風的顯微的玻璃作針
that's under the microscope
那在顯微之間之下
The DNA you hooked this pin
你把這個針勾頂的DNA
Plastic eggs beaten to one cell stage
打到一個細胞期的塑膠卵
Then you don't care about it after typing in
那麼打進去以後你就不管它
let it float
讓它浮發出來
Next, the identification of DNA and the screening of its appearance
再來DNA的鑒定跟它的外型的篩選
Can it grow faster
是不是可以長得比較快
Or are they more resistant to disease?
或是抗病力比較強等等呢
This micro-injection is not the most technical
這個micro-injection它不是最有一個技術
So besides this technology
那麼除了這個技術以外呢
What about the second technique?
第二個技術呢
because we know the egg
因為我們知道這個卵
It's an egg membrane and a cell membrane
它是一個卵膜跟細胞膜
So use the film to create space
所以有用電影創空法
Just use Electoral Polition
就是用Electoral Polition
is to use instantaneous high voltage
就是用瞬間的高電壓
For example, 2000V, 3000V
比如說2000V、3000V
Use the non-second method
用non-second的方法
electrical stimulation
用電的刺激
you put the indented egg
你把縮進卵
Soak in the hands of straight DNA
泡在直體DNA的手持裡面
easy inside
容易裡面
After electrical stimulation
電刺激以後
The cell membrane will fluctuate momentarily
細胞膜會瞬間有波動產生
DNA goes into the egg
DNA就進到卵裡面去
So this can also achieve fast DNA transfer
所以這樣子也可以達成快速的DNA傳送
soak in the egg
泡在卵裡面去
The third method is to compare artificial cell membranes
第三個方法就是比較人工的細胞膜
That is to say
也就是說
We know that the structure of the cell membrane is a
我們知道細胞膜的結構是一個
gelatin membrane
凝脂酸層的膜
The gelatinous film can be artificially made into a
凝脂膜我們可以用人工的方法做成一個
Pointing style is Legislative Shuang
指直體就是立法爽
So this Lipson, we'll take the DNA,
所以這個Lipson,我們就會把DNA,
Plastid DNA is packed inside this Lipson
質體DNA裝在這個Lipson裡面
So its structural properties are similar to cell membranes
所以它的結構性質跟細胞膜是類似的
then our cells
那麼我們的細胞
then when this, this, this
那麼當這個,這個,這個
What about this plastid?
這個質體呢
Then put it in this, this, this
那麼裝在這個,這個,這個
What's inside this substance?
這個質體裡面呢
What about when it hits the cell membrane?
那麼碰到細胞膜的時候呢
We undergo either electrical stimulation
我們經過要嘛是電的刺激
Either or use, use this
要嘛或者是用,用這個
This PEG is
這個這個PEG就是
The diameter of Polyacin glycol
Polyacin glycol的,的出徑呢
it fuses, the cell membrane fuses
它會融合,細胞膜融合
Then the DNA is sent into the cell
那麼DNA就送到細胞裡面去
this is, this
這個是,這個
It can be achieved by the method of cell membrane fusion
用細胞膜融合的方法可以來達成
What about this commonly used one?
那這一個常用的呢
It is the method of using, using viruses, vectors
是用,用病毒呢,載體的方法
there are some viruses
那有一些病毒呢
it can
它可以呢
Infection, what about the genes of foreign aid?
感染,把外援的基因呢
Through the infection process?
透過感染的程序呢
Then it goes into the cell
那麼會進入到細胞裡面去
For example, like viruses, Novirus
比如說像病毒,Novirus
Then it can be loaded with the genes of foreign aid
那麼它可以裝載外援的基因
So we can put the gene of our foreign aid
那麼能夠把所以我們把我們的這個外援的基因
loaded in this viral vector
裝在這病毒載體
Let it infect this sperm or egg
讓它感染這個精子或是獸精卵
Then the gene can be transmitted in
那麼基因它可以傳送進去
so there are various ways
所以有各種方法
Because the development of scientific research can be re-applied
因為科學的研究的發展都可以再應用
But basically everyone is still the most commonly used
但是基本上大家還是最常用是
with this microcolumn method
用這個顯微柱子的方法
Or this radio wave method to do gene transfer
或者是這個電波的方法來做基因的轉值
then in the research
那麼在研究裡面
Because of Yilie's research
因為儀列的研究
Everyone is trying their best to explore the function of genes
大家也想盡辦法要探討基因的功能
technology that can be combined with genetic modification
可以來結合基因轉值的技術
to study the function of genes
來做研究基因的功能
That was developed first in Iliad
那在儀列先被發展出來
Then Gene proposes several methods
那麼基因提出了幾個方法
Then they are very useful in research
那麼都非常的在研究上面非常有用處
Well, of course I won't go into details on this side.
那麼這一方我當然不細講
Nucleus method with Zinc Finger
有Zinc Finger的Nucleus的方法
Or Titan's method or Christophe Cass
或是Titan的方法或是Christophe Cass
These methods can all cause specific genes
那這些方法都可以造成特定的基因
for example
比如說
So which gene of your fish destroys it
所以說你這個魚類的哪一個基因把它破除以後
What impact would it have to demonstrate the function of these genes
它會產生什麼樣的影響來證明這些基因的功能
We use this technology
我們透過這樣的技術
Let's look at the research on growth promotion
我們來看看成長的促進的研究
what we know best is
我們最了解的就是
Growth of our vertebrates
我們的脊椎動物的生長
It's the regulator that makes the lice nectar
它是做內蝨蜜的調控
the regulation of the endometrium basically it has an axis
內蜜的調控基本上它有一個軸線
It is the square base of growth hormone is GHRH
就是生長荷爾蒙的四方基數就是GHRH
It is secreted by Xia's ball in the brain
是由夏氏球這邊分泌出來在腦部裡面
Xia's ball releases these religion hormones
夏氏球釋放出來這些religion hormone
It is to release the base to the pituitary gland
就是釋放基數送到腦下垂體
The pituitary gland talks about this GHRG4G
腦下垂體就說到這個GHRG4G
It starts to produce growth base is GH
它就開始製造生長基數就是GH
After the growth base is released, it will be sent to the whole body
那生長基數出來以後它要送到全身
especially sent to the liver
尤其是送到肝臟裡面去
What about the liver?
那送到肝臟呢
It attacks this transgenic growth factor in the liver
它又出擊肝臟的這個類移導式生長因素
it also secretes
它也分泌出來
that send to the muscles, bones, organs of the whole body
那送到肌肉、骨骼、全身的器官
So what about this IGF?
所以這個IGF呢
It's been half a year
就半年了
A very important function of promoting cell proliferation
促進細胞增生的一個很重要的功能
So this becomes an axis for the growth of an inner honeyhog
所以這變成一個內蝟蜜生長的一個軸線
So what do we do based on this axis
那麼所以我們根據這個軸線呢
let's discuss
來探討說
So what the hell is Gross Hormone in the fish?
那麼Gross Hormone到底在魚類裡面
to promote growth?
來促進成長呢
How to apply its physiological mechanism to do research
是怎麼樣子可以來應用它的這個生理機制來做研究
That's what I mentioned just now
那剛才我提到就是說呢
through
透過經
The earliest of this growth base
最早的這個生長基礎
What about job transfer?
這個這個轉職呢
into the mouse
是到老鼠裡面的
By 1980
到1980年的時候呢
then it can make the mouse
那麼它可以讓這個老鼠
This Gross Hormone that accepted the outer circularity
接受了外圓性的這個Gross Hormone
It's long
它長體型呢
It's this original this this this this this mouse
是這個原來的這個這個這個這個老鼠
two to three times as large
兩倍到三倍大
Proof that genetic modification
確實證明說基因轉值
The growth technique through gene expression
透過基因表現這個生長技術
It can grow individually
它個體是可以成長的
So this technology is a dream for everyone
所以這個技術大家是 dream
Then we can wave to other animals
那麼我們對其他動物能波
A similar technique can be used
類似的技術可以運用
so this is
所以這個是
the first to meet
第一個會合準的
The growth of idioms
規語的成長
So they put the growth technology
所以他們就把生長技術
get the rules
弄到規語
so at the same time
所以在同樣的時間
It has the greatest difference
它差別度最大的
so big
有這麼大
So of course this should
所以這個當然這個要
Compliance with biosafety assessment
符合生物安全評估
their individual stocks are fixed
他們的個股都有定合
Hingel standard
Hingel標準
That technique has been used
那這樣技術已經被用到
the carp
這個鯉魚
this big
這個大
this is the original
這個是原來的
Or Channel Catfish
或是Channel Catfish
It's an anchovies
就是鱺魚
or turtle fish etc.
或是烏龜魚等等
So to prove a theory like this
所以證明這樣子的理論
with technology it is feasible
跟技術它是可行的
So
那麼
So we first
所以我們先是
also come
也來
Look at this just-like guideline growth factor
看這個剛剛類壹導式生長因子
IGF
IGF
unbroken growth
對無過癒的成長
Then we use this injection or oral method
那麼我們用這個注射或是口服的方法
also prove these
也證明這些
it uses it to compare growth factors
它用它比較生長因子
It promotes growth without heal
它可以促進無過癒的成長
In terms of weight and length
在體重跟體長方面
Probably more than 20%
大概都有超過20%的
Growth and weight gain in ten weeks
在十周裡面有增長跟增重的效用
means that we regulate growth
表示說我們調控生長的
Nemi's system
內蜜的這個系統
Can achieve the effect of promoting growth
可以達成促進生長的效果
Then, due to the development of the genome research
那麼由於基因體的研究發展出來以後
we feel like saying
我們就覺得說
Except IGF
除了IGF以外
Get stimulated by Brosch Hormone
接受Brosch Hormone的刺激
to promote growth
而來促進成長以外
Are there any other factors
還有沒有其他因子
So what we express through our genes
所以我們透過基因表現的
screening of the system
這個系統的篩選
Then we found a new growth factor
那麼我們發現一個新的生長因子
is it coley
是不是科利
Protein premise, the name is a bit longer
蛋白前提,這個名字比較長一點
We call it Provenaning
我們稱為Provenaning
Then this is considered Chinese after typing
那這個認為是國中文打了以後
This granule protein will be expressed if it is
這個顆粒蛋白前提它就會表達出來
that expresses what we think it has to do with growth
那表達出來我們認為它跟生長有關
So we're going to prove it's functional
所以我們要證明它的功能
We transfer to this zebrafish through the elite
我們透過精英轉職到這個斑馬魚
so so live a carrier
那麼所以過著一個載體
Then after elite transfer
那麼經過精英轉職以後
It is also found that whether public
也確實發現不管是公的
or female zebrafish
或是母的斑馬魚
If elites who exhibit this granulin premise
如果表現這個顆粒蛋白前提的精英
words that can show
可以表現出來的話
It can gain up to 48% of its body weight
它體重可以增加到48%
Weight can be increased by 18.6% or 13.6%
體重可以增加18.6%或是13.6%
So there is a function like this
所以有這樣的功能
So of course we're going to talk about it
那麼我們當然要探討它
Mechanisms through which cellular transmission
透過什麼樣子細胞傳遞的機制
to allow muscles to accelerate growth
來讓肌肉可以來加速成長
So we also identify it after MET
所以我們也identify它經過MET
The growth of COVID-19 outbound
新冠肺炎出境的成長
The second is disease
第二個就是疾病
We know that Taiwan raises dead panfish
我們知道台灣養死班魚
is the most famous internationally
是國際上是最有名的
Vaccines for Dead Squid
死班魚的疫苗
often die from viral infection
常常因為病毒的感染而死亡
in the vaccine phase
在疫苗階段
It is the stage of corruption
就是腐化出來的階段
Most important viral infection of the nerve necrosis virus
最重要病毒神經的壞死病毒的感染
So we check for it
所以我們就針對它的檢測
Research on vaccines related to novel RNA
跟新型的RNA的疫苗的研究
We did some new research
我們做了一些新的探討
neuronecrosis virus
這個神經壞死病毒
Almost a vaccine against dead panfish
幾乎對死班魚的疫苗
in the fisherman's stage
在漁花的階段
90% or even 90% will die
會90%甚至90%死亡
So immigration has always existed
所以移民一直是存在的
So how can we develop healthy vaccines
所以如何能夠培養健康的疫苗
is an important subject
是一個重要的課題
So for vaccine development
所以對於疫苗的發展
becomes a
就變成一個
Vaccination is an important issue for viral infection
疫苗這個病毒感染的重要課題
So this becomes an industry
所以這種變成一個產業
but you have to avoid some research
但是你要避幾水研究
fish immune system
就魚的免疫系統
to be able to understand
那要能夠了解
So I won't go into details
所以這些不再細講
It really can become an industry
它確實是可以變成一個產業
then another
那麼另外一個
People or pigs or chickens
人或是豬啊 雞啊
You can keep playing for a second
你一秒可以一直一直打
It is very troublesome to keep fighting fish
魚要一直打是非常麻煩的
If you grab it, it won't collapse
你要抓起來它就不崩跳
maybe it's possible
可能就可能
under too much pressure
受到太大壓力太大
so go to the body
所以就往到身體
it cannot adapt to life and death
它不能適應生死亡
So I must develop
所以我一定要發展出來
no injection
不用注射法
is it possible to use this
是不是可以用這個
deduction method
扣乎的方法來進行
So we have something like this
所以我們就有這樣的目標
so we put
所以我們就把
The vaccine is loaded in the
疫苗裝載在剛剛講的
This nanoscale
這個奈米級的
This Lipso
這個Lipso
Feed this zebrafish inside
裡面餵食這個斑馬魚
then we have this one time
那麼我們這個一個時間
Then I saw this red and silver light, which means it has eaten it.
然後就看到這個紅銀光表示它吃進去
Then after 20 hours still
那麼經過20小時還在
In those 28 hours, it will slowly go to other parts of the body
那28小時慢慢它就會跑到身體的其他地方去
place to go
地方去
means that we use nanoscale
表示我們用奈米級的
this this topic
這個這個指題
then you can put
那麼可以把
through
透過
The absorption of Tibetan coins can enter
藏幣的吸收呢可以進入
inside the body for teleportation
遺體裡面去做傳送
So we put this virus
所以呢我們就把這樣的病毒
fragment of this RNA
的這個RNA的片段
Then as the development of vaccines
那麼作為疫苗的發展
So
那麼
selected a different segment
選了不同的片段
Then look at its ability to resist disease
那麼看看它抗病的這個能力
So we use this intrusive
所以我們用這個干擾性的
the nucleic acid
這個核酸的
What about RNA vaccines?
RNA的疫苗呢
So
那麼
if this virus
如果這個病毒
to infect
來感染
Shiban can do this too
這個這個施班也有辦法
Its survival rate is 39%
它存活率是39%
What about the treatment of the RNA of the Kouwu vaccine?
經過這個口吳疫苗的RNA的這個處理呢
survival rate
存活率
can be increased to 67%
可以提升到67%
This is what we are declaring
這個我們在宣示呢
can be seen
可以看到
new like this
這樣子的新的
Development of Vaccine and Delivery Technology
疫苗跟傳送的技術的發展
can come come come
可以來來來
But how much virus
但是病毒到底量多少
With a company that has this reduction technology
跟一家公司有此減量的技術
comparative physical techniques
比較物理的技術
Simply put, it uses iron oxide
簡單來講就是它用氧化鐵
Becoming a Nanoscale Chef
做成奈米級的廚師
The chef can pick up the antibody of the virus
廚師上面可以接病毒的抗體
Antibodies will catch the virus
抗體它就會抓病毒
So catch more viruses
所以抓病毒越多
This magnet is iron oxide
這個磁鐵它是氧化鐵
When starting in the magnetic field
在磁場裡面開始的時候
turning fast
轉動速度很快
It is of course combined with the virus later
它當然聯合病毒以後
it turns slower
它就轉動變慢
So we can use this technique to quantify
所以我們用這樣的技術可以來定量
This technology must be used now
這個技術就要跟現在用的
The thorough network method of immune nucleic acid is different
免疫的核酸的徹底網法不一樣
and faster
而且速度更快
So this company it has
所以這家公司它已經
Or foreign virus testing
或是國外的病毒檢測
The platform of instruments and services
儀器跟服務的這個平台
The third thing to talk about is
第三個跟歸來談就是
like winter
像冬天
Taiwan is often
台灣常常就是
No milkfish, no abalone
虱目魚啦 無鮑魚啦
This grouper is dying in large numbers
這個石斑魚就是大量死亡
sea ​​scales and so on
海鱗的等等
what about this situation
那麼這個情況呢
just because of the low temperature
就是因為低溫
if continued
如果持續的
heaven smokes above
天堂起煙以上
our farm animals
我們這些養殖物
Responsible for great loss
負責會損失非常大
this mass death
這大量死亡
So let's think about it
所以我們就去想這個問題
some fish are ugly
那有些魚是很看難的
Let's say we know
比如說我們知道
like a carp it is just very ugly
像鯉魚它就是非常看難
you are still in winter
你在冬天它還是在
So this one in the fish tooth is living happily
所以魚齒裡面這個活得很愉快
so we think
所以我們認為
Like sea scales, without abalone, life is hard to see
像海鱗啦 無鮑魚 生命不看難耶
because of its genetic
是因為它的基因跟
one
一個
So we try to say
所以我們就想辦法說
prove that
證明說
which genes
有哪一些基因
genes associated with ugly
跟看難有關的基因
fish
魚
Then we filter through the genes
那麼我們透過基因的篩選
transfer of genes
然後基因的轉持
and then prove that
然後再證明說
this
這個
which genes
是哪一些基因
It's related to the unsightly appearance of fish
是跟魚類的看難有關
Through this research we
我們透過這樣的研究
In fact, we can identify it
其實我們可以identify出來
One base acid for muscle beauty
肌肉的一個基酸肌美
special form
特別的form
Especially the form of M3
特別是M3的form
under low temperature
在低溫之下
it allows zebrafish
它可以讓斑馬魚
improve its resistance
可以增進它的抗含力
So we use a graph like this to say
所以我們就用這樣的圖說
zebrafish
我們把斑馬魚
Wild cooking and gene transfer cooking this base acid muscle beauty
野生煮跟基因轉煮這個基酸肌美
bring it down to 13 degrees C
把它降到13度C
this boiled fish
這一煮的魚
it passes a minute
它經過一分鐘
look at its fish
你看它的魚
It barely moves the pattern
它幾乎pattern都沒有動
that is
就是
Sure enough, there is no fixed file
果然沒定檔
But the genetically modified fish
但是基因轉煮這個基酸肌美的魚
This pattern keeps changing
這pattern一直在變動
It means that fish can adapt to this low temperature
表示說魚它是可以適應這個低溫
So specific numbers
所以具體的數目字
Wild fish at 13 degrees C it only
野生魚在13度C它只有
we measure
我們測量
Its length is the perpetual motion of 20 centimeters
它的長度才是永動它20公分
But genetically modified it can move 190 centimeters forever
但是基因轉煮它可以永動190公分
Indicates that it has acquired the ability to resist containing
表示它獲得了抗含的能力
because it provides enough energy
是因為它提供足夠的能量
make it this movement
讓它的這個運動
As far as positive exercise can be maintained
就積受的運動可以維持
Of course it starts from this energy
那當然這是從這個能量的著手
So we know that this fish
那麼我們知道這個魚類
especially the sea fish
尤其是是分海的魚類
What about ocean fish?
海洋的魚類呢
It's this OmegaSpray
它的這個OmegaSpray
Very large
海量特別多
That's like we know the turtle fish below
那像我們知道下面這個龜魚的
Other fish OmegaSpray
等魚類OmegaSpray
It is EPA DHA
就是EPA DHA
Most oils with DHA are especially rich
DHA最類的油脂特別多
So it has something to do with the anti-sea
所以它是跟抗海有關係的
At the same time it has the function of improving our human health
同時它有增進我們人類健康的這個
This effect has been very
這個功效已經非常的
proved very clearly
證明得非常清楚
Sorry
Sorry
that we often say
那我們常常講的
EPA it's twenty carbons
EPA它是二十個碳
There are five from this
有五個從這個
left this
左這個
Kabocha Look like
卡博抄 Look like
Combination with five double swords
有五個雙劍的組合
This is the EPA
這是EPA
to DHA is 22 carbons
到DHA是22個碳
It N3 has a combination of six double swords
它N3有六個雙劍的組合
So these two types of Omega3
所以這兩類的Omega3
proved
已經證明
This is positive
這個正向來講
For example, toddlers
比如說對陰幼兒
DHA is very important for brain development
DHA對腦的發育非常重要
or health care for eyesight
或者說對視力的保健
also very important
也非常重要
but for disease
但是對於疾病方面
prevent neovascular disease
預防新血管疾病
Prevention of Excellence
預防優異症
prevent slow cancer
預防減緩癌症
or resistance garden
或者是抵抗花園
or anti-brainization
或是防腦化
Finally, there are specific numbers
最終都有具體的數字
so the tv turns on
所以電視打開
Both advertise EPA and DHA
都有在廣告EPA跟DHA
U2 turned out to be interesting
U2原來有趣
I don't talk about which one
我不講哪一個
what kind of sword
什麼劍的
Omega3 is about to advertise
Omega3它就要做廣告
They say in Taiwan
他們說在台灣的
sell fish oil in food
在食品裡面賣魚油
Is it to be bought or written
是要買好的或是成文好的
it is in taiwan
它是在台灣
The other party is selling the third
對方是賣第三位的
So there are many people who say they eat fish oil
所以表示吃魚油的人很多
But if we start from this
但是我們如果從這個
Get it from this food
這個食物裡面獲取
is more important
才是更主要的
then let's discuss
那我們就去探討說
Synthetic EPA and DHA
合成EPA跟DHA
Where is the PASWARE it synthesized
它合成的PASWARE在哪裡
then we're going to discuss
那麼我們就要去探討
Well this is already proven
那麼這個已經很證明
That is to say, in the liver
就是說有在肝臟裡面
to synthesize EPA and DHA
來合成EPA跟DHA
Then also through fat loss beauty
那麼也透過去脂肪美
or go fishy
或去腥美
Drive with this delicious food
跟這個炎腸美來帶動
From this Sparktan
從這個Sparktan的
This Nino-Legacy
這個Nino-Legacy
from vegetable oil
從植物油裡面有
EPA that can be turned into 20 carbons
可以變成20個碳的EPA
With 22 carbon DHA
跟22個碳的DHA
This N is Omega3
這個N就是Omega3
So so we use genetic modification
那麼所以我們就透過基因轉值
Yanchangmei is combined with the still fund Meilai of different styles
延長美跟不同風的依然基金美來結合
So we set up different gene transfer values
所以我們就建立了不同的基因轉值
Let it be able to express the Diata IV, Diata V, and Diata VI just mentioned, and still come in from the fund
讓它能夠表現剛剛提到的Diata IV,Diata V,Diata VI,依然基金美來進來
We use molecular sound, electric current to prove its existence and gene expression
我們用分子聲,電流往往證明它的存在跟基因表現
It's important that we measure the zebrafish we've transferred
那重要的就是我們要來測定我們轉值過的斑馬魚
EPA DHA, and its intermediate EPA
EPA DHA,還有它中間體EPA
This is WallTimes
這個是WallTimes
As a result, the amount of transfer value can be increased several times
我們結果轉值的量可以增加好幾倍
It can be increased to 3 times to 5 times, which is probably the established number
可以增加到3倍到5倍的量,大概是成立的數目
That's a published paper, and its performance is very low compared to ours
那是已經發表論文,它表現量都很低過於我們的
So we can behave like this to fish like this
所以我們就對這樣子的魚能夠表現這樣子
Gene expression we have unique place
基因表現我們有獨特的地方
Then through this performance
那麼透過這樣的表現
Then let's see if this can increase
那麼我們看看這個能不能夠增加
its disease resistance
它的抗病的能力
Just now has the ability to improve anti-inflammation and anti-disease
剛剛有提像抗發炎抗病的能力
So this graph tells us that
所以這個圖告訴我們就是說
Omega-3 job transfer language
有Omega-3的轉職語
It is strong against trauma
它對創傷伏勁
is the viability of the VIP infection
就是VIP的感染的存活力
18% can be increased to 80%
有18%可以提升到80%
So disease resistance increases
所以抗病增加
Resistance to staining at 12 degrees C
對抗染力在12度C
It turns out that the death power is almost 100%
原來死亡力是幾乎100%
Then it can be raised to a survivable temperature
那麼可以提升到可以存活的溫度
So this indeed introduces the gene for Omega-3 synthesis
所以這個確實把Omega-3合成的基因導入以後
Then it not only can increase the amount of EPA
那麼它不但EPA列起量可以增加
At the same time, it improves the disease resistance and infection resistance of the animal
同時增進娛樂的抗病跟抗染力
More importantly, our purpose is the future
更重要我們的目的是將來
These transfers look like a
這些轉職的樣子一種
Can we provide our
我們是不是可以提供我們
EPA and DHA for good health
健康所需的EPA跟DHA
So increasing the body would have no national benefit
所以增加本來無國益體內
is synthetic without EPA DHA
是沒有EPA DHA的合成的
Will it be available in the future
那將來是不是可以提供
source of this
這樣子的來源
Here's what we're going to do next
這是我們之後的構想
The fifth item we are talking about now is the viewing instrument
那第五項我們現在講的是觀賞儀
The viewing instrument may be more pleasing to everyone.
那觀賞儀大家可能比較賞心業務
The industry of this ornamental instrument in Taiwan
那台灣的這個觀賞儀的產業
Then there are currently about four or five billion in output value.
那麼目前大概有四五十億的產值
That's pretty impressive
那麼算是相當的可觀
then the industry
那麼這個產業
The government especially in Pingtung's National Agricultural Biotechnology Park
政府特別在屏東的國家農業生技園區
It is the center of gravity of an ornamental instrument
算是一個觀賞儀的這個重心
then raise it there
那麼在那邊養
Quarantine clearance over there
在那邊檢疫通關
Kaohsiung
那直接由高雄
Not by Kaohsiung Tiny Airport
不是由高雄小小機場
directly to countries around the world
就直接送到世界各國去
I hope that Taiwan's technology for Impression is quite
那希望台灣對於印象的技術相當
In this officialdom in Taiwan, there are people from all over the world
台灣的這個官場裡面,世界上有各地內
It must be in the hands of the electrician within 72 hours
72小時內一定到電戶的手中
So so, this one like this
那麼所以呢,這樣子的這個
This has production and sales in a park in a country
這個有產銷在一個國家的園區裡面
it is a very important part
它是一個很重要的一環
So so such a technique
那麼所以這樣的技術
is genetically modified from Molecular Biology
是從分子生物基因轉值
It has been developing all the way
這樣一直一路發展下來
So about 10 years ago
那麼大概10年前呢
this this this this
這個這個這個這個
As for the Taiwan and Hong Kong company, it took this silver
台港公司呢,它就把這個銀光的
As far as the green silver light, turn until the rice field chair
就綠色的銀光,轉直到稻田椅
So it led to this and this in Taiwan
所以就帶動了台灣的這個這個
The development of this industry of turning straight silver chairs
轉直銀光椅的這個產業的這個發展
So what about this command company in Pingtung?
那麼這個在屏東的這個指令公司呢
know that we have genetic modification and
知道我們有有是基因轉值跟
this gene this this this
這個基因這個這個這個
What about the silver gene?
銀光的基因呢
Then transfer these genes to medium-sized
那麼就把這些基因轉直到中型的
For example, Angelfish, Jiujianpolou
比如說,神仙魚,九間坡樓
or
或者是
This is another fish
這是其他的魚種
Such fish species are the most leading in the world
這樣的魚種是在世界是最領先
And it has attracted the attention of the media of various countries
而且受到各國媒體的重視
just to report
也光以報導
So
那麼
Hey, it's so slow
欸 弄那麼慢
that's pink
那這是桃紅色的
genes from coral
從珊瑚來的基因
go to angelfish
轉直到神仙魚
then changed the color of the fish
那麼改變了這個魚的顏色
I'm not advertising for the company
我不是替公司廣告
I brought his video
我是拿他的影片來
so everyone
所以大家
inside
在裡面
to the point
到點要竟然
with different fluorescent proteins
用不同的螢光蛋白
At present, fluorescent ornamental fish with two viewing modes, day and night, have been released
目前已發出日夜兩種觀賞模式的螢光觀賞魚
in the exploration of life
在生命探索方面
Fluorescent fish not only have aquarium ornamental value
螢光魚不但具有水族觀賞價值
In academic research with the help of fluorescent fish
在學術研究上藉由螢光魚
Come to understand the high-tech genetic engineering and gene transfer technology
來了解高科技的基因工程與基因轉職技術
And explore and learn the mysteries of biotechnology
並從中探索及學習生物科技的奧秘
in drug research
在藥物研究方面
Using gene transfer technology to do drug research
利用基因轉職技術做藥物方面的研究
Can be used in biological therapy in the future
未來可運用在生物治療上
in medical research
在醫學研究方面
Fluorescent fish can grow organs that glow in specific parts
螢光魚能夠培育出特定部位能發螢光的器官
such as heart, liver
如心臟、肝臟
To observe the evolution of the disease and the use of drugs
藉此觀察疾病的演變及藥物的使用
is it effective
是否有效
Agricultural biotechnology is a hot new industry
農業生技為熱門的新型產業
Estimated four years later
預估四年後
The global agricultural production technology output value will reach 63 billion US dollars
全球農業生技產值會高達630億美元
is a new trend in global agriculture
是全球農業的新趨勢
Taiwan is appreciating the difference in biotechnology
台灣在觀賞於生技差異
Strong potential and advantages in industrial development
產業的發展上有強大潛能與優勢
in government support
在政府的支持
and the technical integration support of the Agricultural Biotechnology Industrialization Promotion Office
及農業生物技術產業化推動辦公室的技術整合支援之下
There will be huge business opportunities in the international market in the future
未來在國際市場上會具有龐大的商機
OK so let me explain
OK 所以讓大家了解說
Computing from lab research
從實驗室的研究計算
Indeed, the industry
確實是讓這個產業
They find new business opportunities to develop
他們找到新的商機去發展
But just now the vice president mentioned that
但是剛才副院長有提到說
If this fish is still the next generation
這魚 如果還下一代
If he buys it once, he won't buy it
他買一次他就不買了
It is more important to comply with biosafety issues
更重要的是要符合生物安全的問題
Can not affect the ecology
不能夠影響生態
So for these unlucky platforms
所以對於這些不運的平台
Required for applications in genetically engineered and modified fish
對於應用在基因和改造的魚是必須的
And it is required by the regulations
而且法規上面是它是要求的
so gene transfer you run outside
所以基因轉移你跑到外面去
Of course it will affect the ecology
當然會影響生態
everyone knows
大家知道的
To be able to prevent it from affecting the environment and ecology
要能夠來防止它影響環境生態
in case it escapes to wild conditions
在萬一它與外逃到野外條件的時候
so let's think
所以我們就來思考
In this reproductive line of the flower chair system
在這個生殖線的花椅的系統
what's so special about fish
魚類有什麼特別的地方
When the fertilized eggs of fish start to wear flower chairs
魚類它受精卵開始佩胎花椅的時候
it has this dead germ cell
它有這個死機的生殖細胞
germ cell precursor
就是生殖細胞的前身
It is in the early stage of this flower chair
它在這個佩胎花椅的前期
Cells in these PGCs begin to differentiate
細胞在這些PGC的細胞開始分化
After these 20 days
這些經過20天以後
It differentiates and begins to resemble orgasm
它就分化就開始要類似精潮
egg trough structure
卵槽的結構產生
before the sex ropes
在性繩索之前
It will be turned into a sperm and egg trough
它就會被變成精潮跟卵槽
egg trough
卵槽就產生卵
essence
精槽就產生精質
is such a layered
就是這樣的一層性
so can we try again
所以我們是不是能夠再試試的
Cells in PGC
在PGC的細胞
or soft cells
或是軟的細胞呢
Expression of this specific gene using Molecular Biology
用分子生物的表達這個特定的基因
If its cells can destroy it
把它細胞可以把它破壞的話呢
What about a fish like you it won't become non-hard
你這樣的魚呢它就不會變成不硬
But the female fish has to be able to get pregnant
但是母魚要能夠懷孕啊
So this system is to be able to control the verbal
所以這個系統就是要能夠口條控式的
This expression of this gene
這個基因的這個表現
So there is a kind of fish that can live forever
所以有種魚是可以一直活的
Then do a specific treatment for the fish you want to sell
那麼你要賣的魚再做一個特定的這個處理
performance with enzymes
用酵素的表現
or lighting method to deal with
或是光照的方法來處理
So we develop two methods
所以我們就發展兩個方法呢
So let's destroy its PCC
那麼來破壞它的PCC
One is the method of blowing with enzymes
一個是用酵素吹化的方法
we one this this
我們一個這個這個
Make it not easy to dampen the beauty of the ring
讓它不容易消激環的美
import into this glowfish
導入到這個螢光魚
So this blowing with this enzyme
所以用這個酵素的這個吹化呢
What about making PCC cells
那可以讓PCC的細胞呢
it will kill it
它會把它殺死掉
So there is no doubt about ejaculation or soft tide
所以精潮或是軟潮就不懷疑
or we express luminal protein to it
或是我們給它表現光明蛋白
photo sensitive protein
photo sensitive protein
it is irradiated with red light
它經過紅光的照射
it will sharpen the free machine out
它會激化自由機出來
also kills cells, soft cells
也會把細胞殺死 軟細胞殺死
So the result of our approach like this
所以我們這樣子的approach的結果
You can probably see the final result
大概可以看到最後的結果
Elimination cyclase
就是剛剛用消基環聯酶
to stimulate
去刺激的時候
normal female soft
正常的母魚的軟
full of health
保滿 滿健康的
In fact, you can see one by one
其實可以看到一粒一粒
But after soaking in this machine
但是經過這個機子的浸泡
cyclase
來鑄使這個消基環聯酶
This is when Nitro Reductase comes into play
就是Nitro Reductase來作用的時候
Its metabolites let soft cells kill
它代謝物就讓軟細胞殺死
Therefore, soft frying will shrink and have no business force
所以軟炒就萎縮 不具生意力
Bright protein is the same
光明蛋白也是一樣
As a result, after the light is illuminated, after the red light is illuminated
結果照光以後 照紅光以後
Shrink after soft frying
軟炒就萎縮
This is a normal soft fry
這是正常的軟炒
So in this way it can be achieved
所以用這樣的方式可以達到
Should not control
不應的控制
However, we also cooperate with the industry for unsuitable technologies.
但是不應的技術我們也是跟業界合作
Inappropriate off-coder and normal help
不應的關碼儀跟正常的幫助
it is exactly the same
它是一模一樣的
The color, body shape, vitality, health and sobriety are exactly the same
顏色、體型、活泡度、健康清醒是一模一樣的
So we hope that technology like this in the industry can enter this market
所以我們就希望業界這樣子的技術可以進入這個市場
Just mentioned why GMO is doing this biosafety assessment
剛剛提到為什麼GMO要做這個生安全評估
Because one is concerns about environmental biosafety assessment
因為一個是顧慮環境生物安全評估
This is usually managed by the Council of Agriculture
這通常都是農委會在管
In foreign countries, plus the Environmental Protection Agency will govern this part
在外國會再加上環保署會來管治這個部分
if you want to eat
如果要吃的
In the past, health was first and foremost the Ministry of Health and Welfare
以前衛生首先是衛福部
It is to manage this food safety
它要管理這個食品安全
Both must be eligible for gold transfer
兩項都要符合金轉職的
If you are an official
如果做官商的
As long as the Council of Agriculture and the Environmental Protection Agency can agree
只要農委會和環保署他們就可以同意
If you want to use food, you still have to go through the food hygiene control of the Ministry of Health and Welfare
如果要用吃的就還是經過衛福部的食品衛生管制
Only after passing the test can it be used
測試合格才可以來用
Therefore, these studies must return to basic research
所以這些的研究都要回歸到基礎研究
Then our basic research
那麼我們基礎研究
i feel full
我覺得滿有
That is to say
有心得的就是說呢
Doing fish research always thinks
做魚的研究去都是認為
Fish research is relatively backward
做魚的研究都是比較落在
Behind the scenes of doing mouse studies
做老鼠的研究的後面
but 30 years ago
但是在30年前呢
That's starting to see the zebrafish feature
那開始看到斑馬魚的特色
that can be used as a model animal
那可以作為一個模式動物
So what about the zebrafish?
所以這個斑馬魚呢
It has several characteristics
它的特色有幾種
It's its plastic egg
就是它的塑膚卵呢
it is transparent
它是透明的
So it's an outside mouse again?
所以又是體外的老鼠呢
You can watch the change of its fluid at any time
你隨時可以看它化液的變化
to the formation of organs
到器官的形成
So these two days the fish floated out
所以這兩天魚就浮發出來
What about when the first day is over?
那麼到第一天完事結束的時候呢
Happy to have some organs
有一些器官就開心了
Like the heart starts to drop
比如心臟開始掉了
Then its blood starts to flow and so on
那麼它的這個血液開始流通等等
these can see this
這些就可以看到這個
what about the fish
那麼它魚呢
It not only has a short melting time
它的不但化液時短
It can make it soft every week
它每個禮拜可以讓它傳軟
Every week can send soft
每個禮拜可以傳軟
200 to 400 pieces
200顆到400顆
so what time
所以呢做時間
Material
材料
I even extended this piece to primary and secondary education
甚至我把這一塊推廣到中小學的教育
You don't have to kill frogs before
就不必在以前殺青蛙
Then it's cruel to do these floral research, isn't it?
然後是這個蠻殘忍做這些花藝的研究對不對
Now my name is Taiken Corporation
現在我這個叫台肯公司
It was developed as a teaching material for primary and secondary schools
它就發展作為中小學的教材
Do it with this zebra chair
用這個斑馬椅來做
because we have to
因為我們要做
Are zebra chairs the same as people?
說斑馬椅到底跟人是不是一樣
This is a very important subject
這個是非常重要的這個課題
You want to be a model animal to study human diseases
你要做一個模式動物來研究人類的疾病
So in terms of cancer
那麼這就在癌症方面來講
Let's say it's human
比如說這個是人類的
Pathology section of this different cancer
這個不同的癌症的病理切片
this is the zebra chair
這是斑馬椅的
You can use this type of long way
你可以看用這個長道種類好了
Then it's almost very similar to
那這幾乎非常類似
or this clinical cell carcinoma
或是這個臨狀的細胞癌
Its structure is something like
它的結構就是類似
The pathological mechanism is also similar to
病理機制它也類似
So the zebra chair was created to be an animal for human diseases
所以就機起了斑馬椅的做人類疾病的動物
Some kind of disease, I think besides the disease of the lungs
類有的疾病 我想除了說肺的疾病以外
Is it because it is a language that breathes with gills?
因為它是語是用腮呼吸嘛
Other probably you see these physical diseases
其他大概你看這些生理的疾病
including mental illness or toxicity
包括精神的疾病或是毒性方面都是
Dr. Ma can provide us with good
幫馬醫師都可以提供我們很好的
The material of this study so the new technology of these studies
這研究的素材 所以這些研究的新的技術
Functional research and development have also constructed a very complete
功能的研究發展也建構了非常完成
Academia Sinica takes the lead in developing different technologies in China
中研院是帶頭在國內來發展不同的技術
Reporting to you means that Congress will support it.
跟貴報告就是說 國會也就支持
Our Academia Sinica built a core facility for horse medicine
我們中研院弄了一個幫馬醫的核心設施
So we use the core of Academia Sinica
所以我們用中研院這個核心
Like a laboratory in Taiwan that helps horse medicine do research
像全台幫馬醫做研究的實驗室
We counted 110
我們統計了有110個
that's quite a lot
那可以說是相當的多
We feel that there are so many research teams like this in Taiwan
我們覺得像這樣的研究的團隊在台灣這麼多
is it possible
是不是可以
It can be used to present our Taiwan application on the neighbor’s house
可以來呈現我們台灣的在鄰居房上面的應用
Is that actually
那事實上有沒有
In fact there is already this system
事實上已經有這個系統
Intervention as a drug screen using zebrafish
用斑馬魚來介入作為藥物的篩選
Then these foreign laboratories
那麼這些有國外的實驗室
Or the pharmaceutical company has already done
或是藥廠已經做
There is no way this small Taiwanese kitchen can do it
台灣這個小廚館沒有辦法做到
This high-throughput screening
這個高通量的篩選
Usually, our drug screening is to use cells to screen
那通常我們藥物篩選就是用細胞去篩選
its efficacy or toxicity test
它的有效性或是毒性測試
Then jump to the mouse experiment
然後就會跳到老鼠的試驗
But the cost of experimenting with this intermediate mouse is very high
但是這個中間老鼠的試驗成本非常高
And the requirements for animal support are also very strict.
而且動物扶植的要求也非常嚴
So now I have a new idea
所以現在已經有新的一個想法
from cell culture screening
就是從細胞培養的篩選
Before entering the experimental animal screening of mice
進入老鼠的實驗動物篩選之前
can help barbarian fish can intervene
可以幫蠻魚可以介入
Speed ​​up and reduce costs
加速以外還減少成本
So let’s talk about the object of this screening
所以可以先說這個篩選的對象
Say from 1000 you win 1000 screenings
比如說從1000個你贏了1000個篩選
You can help the fish
你幫蠻魚可以
you take 100 tests
你拿100個測試
Among them, the best 12 need compounds
其中可能最好12個的need compound
Only after entering the system of Oster
才進入奧斯德的系統
so the system
所以這個系統
Zebra Doctor's screening system has entered such a stage
斑馬醫的篩檢系統已經進入這樣的階段
So a couple of examples
所以有幾兩個例子
one is
一個就是
this suppression
這個抑制
active ink
比如說主動墨
Talk to Zai about this medicine
找宰說這個藥
this chemical
這個chemical
this is
這個是
it has zebra doctor pattern
它有斑馬醫的模式
It is similar to the main plug of our blood vessels
它類似我們這個血管的主塞
So the blood can't get out
所以血液打不出去
After soaking it with this medicine, the blood cleared
這藥給它浸泡以後血液通了
So this color means the blood vessels are circulating
所以這粒色代表血管在流通
This means that such a drug
這表示這樣子的藥
It is indeed possible to re-live the situation that Mo Zai said actively
它確實是可以讓主動墨宰說的狀況可以re-live
the second is
第二個就是
particle means
粒子就是說
This medicine it's a Tyrotin-Kan's inhibitor
這個藥它是一個Tyrotin-Kan's inhibitor
That's actually a medicine
那這其實是一個藥
it can suppress this
它可以來抑制這個
anti-angiogenesis
這個抗血管的生長
Because of cancer you also want blood vessels not to regenerate
因為癌症你同時希望它血管不能夠再增生
Tissue from cancer cells shrinks
癌症細胞的組織會萎縮
So this is a normal vessel aorta
所以這個是正常的血管主動脈
Then the branching vessels
然後分支的血管
After getting this medicine in
那這個藥弄進去以後
Some blood vessels are different
有些血管就不同了
Said that this can be directly analyzed by image
表示說這個可以直接用影像分析
Let's see if the medicine works
就可以看這個藥有沒有效果
This is an in vivo effect that can be observed with zebrafish
這是活體的效果用斑馬魚可以來觀測
So like this I'm giving two examples
所以像這樣我是舉兩個例子
So many automated systems have been developed
所以就很多自動化的系統就已經發展出來
then i will say too fast
那麼我很快就過速就說
Then our Sense is more interested in the liver
那我們Sense對肝臟比較有興趣
Because the flower chair of Urman's liver is made by very few people
因為Urman肝臟的花椅做的人非常少
in fish
在魚類
The second one is related to our Taiwan, especially the liver disease in Taiwan
第二個它跟我們台灣尤其台灣肝的疾病
Aspects of the liver can be linked
肝臟的方面可以連結的關係
So we're going to do live liver
所以我們就去做肝臟的活體
Suspicion of the liver Before we have to find a professional liver
肝臟的懷疑 之前我們先要找到肝臟專業性的
priming mass
表現的一個單白質跟它的啟動質
So the genetic modification on our side
所以我們這邊的基因轉值
The liver is indeed only the liver has pronunciation light
把肝臟確實是只有肝臟有發音光
This way we can directly observe changes in the liver
這樣子我們可以直接觀察肝臟的變化
Is it sick or not? The suspected condition is normal or not.
它有病沒病 懷疑的狀況正常不正常
we can discuss it
我們就可以來做它的探討
If combined with human liver disease
如果結合到人類的肝病
We know that if it's a viral liver disease
我們知道如果是病毒性的肝病的話
Liver that has undergone thick liver and thin liver
經過瀰肝和細肝的肝臟
Liver disease can cause fatty liver
肝臟的疾病會有脂肪肝
hepatitis liver fibrosis
肝炎肝纖維化
If unlucky, it will become cirrhosis
不幸的話就變成肝硬化
Liver cancer
到肝癌就一息息
Is the zebra doctor in these processes disadvantaged?
這些過程斑馬醫是不是有劣勢的狀況
we will establish such a mechanism
我們就建立這樣的機制
Indeed we put this
確實我們把這個
Antigen protein of blood-sucking liver refining or nosebleed liver refining
吸血肝炼或是鼻血肝炼的抗原蛋白質
go to zebrafish
轉直到斑馬魚
when to observe
加以去觀察的時候
Here's what happened to the mouse's liver cancer incarnation
這是老鼠的肝癌化身的情形
from normal
從正常的
hepatic fibrosis
經過止髮肝肝纖維化
Then adenoma tumor and liver cancer
然後腺腫腫瘤跟肝癌
About 68 weeks, about one year and five months
大概要68週 大概一年五個月左右
The zebrafish system we specifically built
斑馬魚的系統我們特別來建立
If it is treated with carcinogenic TAA chemical drugs
如果是有用致癌的TAA化學藥物處理
It is 12 weeks, about three months will produce this ACC
是12週 大概三個月會產生這個ACC
If you want to turn straight to this ACV
如果還要轉直這個ACV
It is the core protein refined by blood-sucking liver
就是吸血肝炼的核心蛋白質的話
About 6 weeks to 8 weeks to see the changes in the organization with ACC
大概6週到8週就看到組織的變化有ACC
So the time is shortened a lot
所以這樣時間縮短非常多
This facilitates our discussion as disease
這有利我們作為疾病的探討
So we also observe
所以我們也觀察到
It's the virus that we use to separate the liver from the liver
就是我們把瀨肝跟吸肝的這個病毒
HBX and HCP are transferred until the zebrafish performs
HBX跟HCP轉直到斑馬魚去表現的時候
We saw that its pathological section showed short tube abnormalities
我們看到它的病理切片是有短管異常情形
Then the short pipe anomaly
那麼這短管異常情形
ICC between us and human
我們跟人類的Human的ICC
This is what we call this short-to-carcinoma ICC in the liver
就是我們叫做這個肝內的短到癌ICC
its unusually short structure
它這不正常的短到的結構
the pathological conditions are quite similar
是病理狀況是相當的相近
So let's go over the disease pattern study
所以讓我們在疾病模式研究上面
We are very interested in exploring these mechanisms
我們就很有興趣來探討這些機制
When I have a chance, I will report the details to you again.
有機會再跟各位報告這樣的細節
In addition, we have
另外我們對於長到
because our digestive tract
因為我們對消化道
So long that we actually wanted to study
長到我們其實一直想研究
For example, it can be linked to colorectal cancer
比如說可以連動到大腸癌
That research is moving bowel cancer
那研究在動腸癌
We can make this gut only bonus silver
我們可以讓這個腸子只有花紅銀光
we use kongfokou
我們用孔佛口
This is what the Chinese call Kong Fokou
這是孔佛口中國人叫什麼
highway treat
公路對待
This risky technique taught by industry
工業教的這個作險為的技術
Then let's crosscut its long structure
那麼我們就來橫切它長道的結構
So we can see the long tube from different parts
所以我們可以從不同的部位看到長管
It is very uniform and can express red and silver light
它是很均勻的可以表現的紅銀光
So the fish if it has been processed
所以這個魚如果它有經過處理
or genetic changes
或是基因的改變
If there is a tumor on the long road
那麼長道有長腫瘤的話
These changes are coming
這些變化馬上來到
So we can do these experimental studies
所以我們就可以去做這些實驗動的研究
This is the platform we hope to be able to express with the light of the digestive organs
這是我們希望能夠用消化器官的營光表現的平台
Studying the Mechanism from Digestion to Formation
研究消化到形成的機制
we pass this
我們透過這個
So we have built this zebrafish
所以我們這個有建立這個斑馬魚
It is red and silver light
它長道是紅銀光
Dry Tibet is green and silver light
乾藏是綠銀光
the same fish again
再同一條魚
so we can study their two different organs
所以我們可以研究它們兩個不同器官的
The relationship between interaction and disease
互動跟疾病的關係
I'll finish speaking in about ten minutes, okay?
我大概要十分鐘內要講完好不好
We will then
我們就
then industrial innovation
那麼產業創新
this is the government
這個是政府
then please let me take charge of this project
那麼請我負責這個計畫
the adoption of agricultural biotechnology
就是農業生技採用
Promote programs wishing to bring academic research
推動方案 希望把學術研究
Can be imported into the industry
可以導入到產業界
The needs of industry can allow academia to interact
產業界的需求可以讓學術界來互動
So this plan starts from an innovative productization platform
所以這個計畫從創新產品化的平台
We are doing both with commoditization
跟商品化我們都在做
We, the Chinese and British communities, are responsible
由我們中英界來負責
There are various parts to come together to participate
有各部份來共同來參與
We have a calibration focus in aquatic products
我們在水產方面有標定重點
Just mentioned again and again is
剛剛一再提到的就是
Grouper, Taiwan sea bream, ornamental fish and shrimp are our focus
石斑魚 台灣鯛 觀賞魚跟蝦是我們的重點
So there are a lot of successful
所以這些就有很多成功的
Through plan matchmaking and plan transfer
透過計畫的媒合跟計畫的計轉
There are many successful cases to carry out
有很多成功的案例來進行
The grouper industry
石斑魚的產業
There is also the industry chain of sea bream
還有鯛魚的產業鏈
Industrial chain of ornamental fish
觀賞魚的產業鏈
There are already successful companies in the shrimp industry chain
蝦產業鏈都已經有成功的公司
or start making money
或是開始賺錢了
So I'll let it pass quickly on my side
所以我這邊很快就給它經過去
So, for example, this one just talked about molecular markers
那麼比如說這個剛剛講分子標記
Just mentioned there are several techniques to perform
剛剛提到的有幾個技術來進行
Like in addition to the research results of our laboratory
像除了我們實驗室的研究成果以外
we also see
我們這邊還看到
We have combined one of Taiwan's largest companies that export products
我們結合了台灣最大的一個隨產品外銷的公司
And Taiwan is number one and number two
還有台灣算是第一、第二
Belonging to all feed companies
屬於所有的飼料公司
to bring them together
就促成他們結合
A company, a feed company, let it raise fish
一個公司 飼料公司讓它養魚
Then this accompanying product company
那麼這個隨產品公司
It will be processed and exported to the world
它要加工外銷全世界
Therefore, Taiwan Eagle can be established to internationalize its products
所以就成立了台灣雕可以產品國際化
You can learn about companies like this
各位可以了解像這樣子的公司
Big grower he told me
大成長農他告訴我說
He employs more than 1,000 people abroad
他在國外聘用的員工有1000多人
The talents we train in Taiwan are no better than others
我們台灣培養的人才都不過他用
So it can be seen how big the industry they see
所以可見這個產業他們看到的面向是多大
The following aspect has this technique from detecting
下方面有這個技術從檢測到
The disease agrees that he is also close
這個病的同意他也接近來
as well as with Rakyo Marine, which makes the instruments.
還有跟製造儀器的銳基海洋公司
Nazang Nanya did very well
那藏南亞做得非常好
I just talked about the technology that shouldn't be
那剛講了不應的技術
our continuous development
我們的不斷的發展
This is the technology of the fluorescent chair
這個是螢光椅的技術
So let's talk about this technology in particular.
那麼這個技術我們特別講一下就是
Russian Academy of Sciences
俄羅斯的科學院
In the past few years, the Chinese Academy has also booked a cooperative project
在前年來中文學院也訂了合作業
he saw and said
他看到說
My deep sea club wants to build a marine museum
我的在海深會要弄一個海洋博物館
In particular, Taiwan's ornamental instruments will be displayed
特別要展示台灣的觀賞儀
Because seeing Taiwan's innovative technology
因為看到台灣創新的技術
Vaccines Against Emergencies
抗緊迫的疫苗
Detection Reagent
檢測試劑
This technology can use immune weight gain as a data additive
這個技術可以用免疫增重作為資料添加劑
Let's take on this again to talk about his development
再承擔這個要說他發展的
He is only the five companies involved in this plan
他光是這個計轉的五家公司
we count for him
我們給他算
His transfer income has exceeded 50 million
他的計轉金的收入已經超過五千萬
So it can create a lot of output value
所以可以創造產值是非常多
So we hope that such technology can be biased to the
所以我們希望這樣的技術可以偏步到
Can be applied in markets all over the world
全世界的市場裡面可以去應用
augmentation is data
增進是資料的
Transfer and processing
調供加工
DHA is cultured in the early column
DHA在早列培養
This is also the technology achieved by Weidan Company
這也是衛丹公司成績的技術
it has been certified
它已經得到實領認證
Many foreign manufacturers have come to Weidan to say
國外很多大廠都來衛丹說
You are producing DHA very well
你是生產DHA很不錯
Cultivated and extracted from the early column
從早列裡面培養出來 萃取出來的
So it has become an industry
所以已經變成一個產業
Collagen
膠原蛋白
is my past student
是我過去一個學生
his own company
他自創公司
he does diabetic couple
他做糖尿病的夫妻
to apply the growth of entertainment thus
來應用娛樂的生長因此
Can be used as a couple with diabetes
可以作為糖尿病的夫妻的運用
I have entered clinical trials
我已經進入臨床試驗
further
更進一步
turn into medicine
都變到醫學
We also work with this company
我們也跟這家公司合作
Never Too Much Neighbors
從無過於的鄰片
can be extracted
可以萃取
Can make successful angle mold
可以製作成功角模
What about this technique?
那麼這個技術呢
we are training him
我們正在跟他培養說
We want to raise more than 3 kg of five countries fish
我們要養3公斤以上的五國魚
The scales are over and we've seen it
鱗片就過到我們去看過了
Then they plan to compete with Germany this year
那麼他們今年準備跟德國的
Clinical trials at the Faculty of Medicine of the University of Cologne
科隆大學醫學院做臨床試驗
Then we hope that if this works out,
那我們希望這個可以成功的話
to human health
對人類的這個健康
This should be of great help
這個應該是幫忙非常大
So you can't imagine saying
所以大家不能想像說
How can fish things be used by people?
魚的東西怎麼可以用到人
That's because of the collagen in fish scales
那因為魚鱗片的膠原蛋白的結果
it is most like a person
它是跟人的最像
The first, the second, fish and man
第一個 第二個 魚跟人
it has no common infectious disease
它沒有共通的傳染病
It's a virus
就是病毒
So its safety is higher than other animal sources
所以它的安全性高過於其他的動物來源
So they have this consideration
所以它們有這樣的考量
Then as cosmetics etc.
那麼作為化妝品等等
The third is our aquatic products
第三個就是我們的水產品
We often go abroad
我們常常出國外銷
Although the government has various regulations
雖然政府有各種的規定
We have production and sales experience
這個我們有產銷 履歷
There is also CAS certification
還有CAS認證
Some
一些
Only then can ordinary people and consumers be able to use it domestically
那麽才能夠國內讓老百姓、消費者能夠去運用
But there are different certifications in foreign countries
但是外國還有不同的認證
For example, the European Union has ASC certification
比如說歐盟它有ASC的認證
North America is also this Europe and the United States, it has its BAP certification
北美也是這個歐美國它有它的這個BAP的認證
Then our certification is still not up to their certification standards
那我們的認證是還達不到他們的認證標準
Japan has JAS certification
日本有JAS認證
Therefore, food safety certification standards in these countries have various certification standards
所以食品安全這些國家它的認證標準有各種的認證標準
So our Taiwan certification in the past is that this grows fast
所以我們台灣過去認證就是這個長得快
Then the cost is low, and this harmless substance can be used.
然後成本低然後就是這個沒有危害的物質等等就可以
But the international standard it requires is higher
但是國際上面它要求的標準更高
So how to comply with international certification is very important
所以如何符合國際的認證那是非常重要
Another one is for the environment of the earth and for the welfare of animals
更另外一個為了地球的環境為了動物的福祉
for...
為了...
social stability
社會的安定
International farming new crown
國際養殖新冠
Not just Yangyi itself
不只是養儀本身
Certification of our grooming
我們養儀的認證
Have you entered social responsibility
你有沒有進到社會責任
Have you paid attention to the health of the fracture?
你有沒有注重餘裂的健康
with his well being
跟他的福祉
Have you met the food safety requirements
你有沒有達到食品安全的要求
Have you caused damage to the environment
你有沒有對環境造成破壞
Do you meet the standards of the green industry
你是不是符合綠色產業的標準
Wait for these certifications to be added one by one
等等這些認證會一觀一觀一直加出來
So we hope that Taiwan's industry
所以我們希望台灣的產業
Can have an international perspective
能夠有國際的視野
In order to maintain the invincible position of interests
才能夠保持利益不敗之地
Just mentioned these different national certifications
剛剛提到這些不同國家認證
The strictest ones seem to be the European and American markets
最嚴的看起來是歐洲跟美國市場
So we need to get these recognitions
所以我們需要得到這些認可
our chance is there
我們的機會才是會有的
Finally, because of the proposed marine biotechnology
最後因為有建議的海洋生技
Research on the development of industry for us in Taiwan
研究產業的發展對我們台灣
Taiwan's future is very important
台灣的未來非常重要
So our colleagues in many domestic academic circles
所以我們在很多國內學界的同儕
under active efforts
積極的努力之下
We established the Taiwan Society of Marine Biotechnology the year before last
我們在前年成立台灣海洋生物技術學會
So this society
所以這個學會
We did what we learned to do
我們做了學會應該做的事情以外
We are also willing to go to the Fisheries Vocational School
我們還願意到水產職業學校
to his teacher
去給他的老師
Bring them the development of new technologies in marine biotechnology
給他們帶進新的海洋生技方面的科技的發展
I also hope that their students can participate in this kind of event
也希望能夠讓他們學生可以參加這樣子的
laboratory work
實驗室的工作
We also extend to the education of high school vocational education
我們還特別延伸到高中職的教育上面
We will also host the 10th Asia-Pacific Marine Biotechnology Conference in May this year
我們今年五月也會舉辦亞太的海洋生物技術會議第十屆
They have suggested that Taiwan has such a foundation
他們有建議台灣有這樣子的基礎
so i take the responsibility
所以我就承擔一下這個責任
with the domestic academic circles
跟國內學界
to cooperate
來合作
So our positioning is this theme
所以我們定位就是這個主題
not only science
不但是科學
Our new challenges to food, medicine, energy and the environment
我們對食品醫藥能源跟環境的新的挑戰
is the subject of our discussion
是我們很討論的主題
Then in the end, we have to deal with our Taiwan
那麼最後我們對我們台灣這個
What is the prospect of the next life
來生就有什麼展望
So
那麼
run back
跑回去
Sorry
Sorry
we run back
我們跑回去
because of time
因為時間的關係
I hope this is OK
這個我希望OK
so the first
所以第一個
Although we are with what we eat every day
我們雖然是跟我們每天要吃的
eat well
吃得好
eat healthy
吃得健康
This is very important
這是很重要的
so i often say
所以我常常講
we eat delicious food
我們吃到好吃的
Or delicious aquatic products
或者是美味的水產品
all feel very happy
都是覺得非常幸福
People of this generation are better than those of 50 years ago
這一代的人比50年前的
we are the same
我們同樣的
people who only live in Taiwan
只活在台灣的人
So happy
太幸福了
too much, right?
太多了 對不對
you see it so
你看它是這麼
Look at this from snapper, snapper fillet, eel
你看看這種從鯛魚 鯛魚片 鰻魚
right this eel
對不對 這個鱔魚
this perch this oyster this mullet roe
這鱸魚 這個牡蠣 這烏魚子
Grass Shrimp Grouper Milkfish
草蝦 石斑 石木魚
soup mound toad toad
湯丘 蛤蟆 蛤蟆
everything, right?
什麼都有 對不對
very happy very happy
非常幸福 非常幸福
Some people used to eat these
以前這些都是有的人吃的
So our last hope is
所以我們最後的一個希望就是
our marine living resources
我們對海洋生物資源
We must explore through research
我們一定要透過研究進行探索
and understand it
而且了解它
find it this feature
找到它的這個特色
find its mechanism
找到它的這個機制
find it this function
找到它的這個功能
So use biotechnology
那麼所以加以運用生物技術
sustainable development of marine biological resources
才能對海洋生物資源永續的發展
we can achieve this
我們才能達到這樣的目的
We humans live on this earth
我們人類活在這個地球上面
Only then can it be very evil
才能夠很合邪的
There are conditions for this development
很有這個發展的這個條件
To maintain the food and health of such a large population
維持這麼龐大的人口的糧食跟健康
Well this wishes all his distinguished guests
那麼這個祝他所有的貴賓
Then everyone is healthy and happy
那麼大家健康幸福
so auspicious
那麼吉祥如意
Then we hope that our ocean Taiwan
那麼我們希望我們海洋台灣
just active perpetual
只是活躍永續
Then I'll come here with you all to make a conclusion.
那我就跟各位到這邊做一個結束
thank you all
謝謝大家
We are very grateful to researcher Wu Teping
我們很謝謝吳特評研究員
Secretary-General Wu gave us this brilliant speech
吳秘書長給我們做的這個精采的演講
There is a section on this one about aquatic biotechnology
有關於這一個水長生物技術的部分
That's because the content is quite substantial
那因為內容相當的充實
so maybe some of you in the audience
所以可能有一些在座的聽眾
the audience is not very clear
觀眾不是很清楚
so if there are some problems
所以如果有一些問題
we can ask
我們可以說來請教
that if there is
那如果有的話
please raise your hand
請你舉手
And then here's the microphone press the green part
然後這裡有麥克風按綠色的部分
this gentleman please
這一位先生請
Thanks
謝謝
Teacher Wu's very wonderful speech
吳老師非常精彩的演講
There was a place that was very impressive just now
剛剛有一個地方印象很深
That is, Mr. Wu is not just studying
就是吳老師不是光研究
Moreover, it is also noted that the business needs to protect and obtain
而且又注意到商業上要保護獲領
So there is research on this issue of not shipping politics
所以有研究不運政的這個問題
but i thought of saying
但是我想到就是說
we except this
我們除了這個
But besides this technology, Mr. Wu
可是吳老師這邊除了這個技術以外
There are also fluorescent fish
又有螢光魚
Do cornea again
又有做角膜
and nutritious
又有營養品
anti-disease
又有抗疾病
immune to disease
還有抗病免疫
many techniques
很多種技術
None of these technologies seem to
這些技術好像都沒有
Protect it like Buyunzheng
像不運政這樣去保護它
That is to say
也就是說
We sell light fish abroad
我們營光魚賣到國外
people can't reproduce
人家沒辦法繁殖
buy from us again
還要再跟我們買
But the recent corneal technology
可是剛剛的角膜技術
anti-disease technology
抗疾病技術
anticancer technology
抗癌技術
anti virus technology
抗病毒技術
It seems that there is no protection
好像都沒有保護
I just want to ask
我想請教就是
we taiwan
我們台灣
Even Mr. Wu's own technology
甚至說吳老師自己的技術
The protection against the outflow of technology
那對於技術的流出的保護
is there any way
有沒有什麼樣的做法
or measures
或是措施
Thanks
謝謝
The question we ask is that
我們所提的問題就是說
How to protect the technology we develop
我們研發的技術怎麼樣保護
Our biggest concern is exodus
我們最擔心的是外流
good technique good seed outflow
好的技術 好的種子外流
I can't come back after going out
外流以後就回不來了
Instead, it arrived in Taiwan, right?
反而呢 到達我們台灣對不對
What about this situation?
這個狀況呢
Agriculture, forestry, fishery and animal husbandry have all happened
農林漁牧都發生過
then this so
那麼這個 所以
one is to say
一個就是說呢
what about these technologies
這些技術呢
If able to have patent protection
如果能夠具有專利保護的
Then we all encourage the industry to say
那麼我們都是鼓勵業界說
Only those with patent protection will give priority to doing calculations
有專利保護的你才優先去做計算
So this technique
所以這樣子的技術
after it turns around
它轉過去以後呢
What about the technology of its industry?
它產業的技術呢
not easy to lose
就不容易流失
just not easy
只是不容易
People may be able to counterfeit
人家可能可以仿冒
But what about our cooperation in Taiwan?
但是呢 台灣我們的這個合作呢
not a one time cooperation
不是一次的合作
It is attribute forward cooperation
它是屬性往前合作
So work with the industry
所以跟業界合作
industry-leading technology
業界有業界的技術
So we are standing here
所以我們是站在這個
Foundations for Pleasant Research
對於愉烈的研究的基礎
come work with it
來跟它一起合作
So part of the industry
所以產業的部分
We all let the industry pay attention to the development of the district
我們都讓產業界注意區發展
So it is very important to obtain a patent
那麼所以專利的取得是非常重要的
The second is to say that the past patents are all patents
第二個就是說過去的專利都是一項專利
So for example, will you predict
那麼比如說你會不會預總
But your detection of the disease, the development of a disease vaccine
但是你對病的檢測 病疫苗的發展
or additives to test materials, etc.
或是試料的添加物等等
We hope that these key technologies will be integrated
我們是希望這些關鍵技術都整合起來
For example, for this Shiban chair
比如說針對於這個施班椅
We start from the detection of pre-total disease
我們就從預總疾病的檢測
then vaccine development
然後疫苗發展
Then special samples
然後特殊的試料
and breeding environment
還有養殖的環境
We need to integrate several technologies together
我們就要好幾個技術一起整合在一起
system integration
變成系統整合
So if you are just a technical vent
所以你光是一個技術出氣的話
He can't compete with Taiwan abroad
在國外他沒辦法跟台灣競爭
Therefore, the integration of technology is important for the protection of our Taiwan technology
所以技術的整合對於我們台灣的技術的保護
is very important
是非常重要
So this piece must become
所以這一塊一定要變成
teamwork
團體合作
So we just mentioned a few examples
所以我們剛剛提到幾個例子
It was promoted in our fancy office
就是在我們花樣辦公室推的
For example, Dachangcheng and Jiafeng
比如說大成長成跟加豐
These are two companies with different business objectives
這是兩個不同的營業目標的公司
It has different technical expertise
它各有不同技術專長
plus academia collaboration
加上學術界合作
Although it is tied together
雖然它是綁在一起
So if this is the case
所以這樣子的話
You say my Jiafeng this part
你說我這個加豐這個部分
I want to go out and get it
自己要出去弄
The part about adopting an aunt does not have a source of good aunts
養姨的部分它沒有好姨後來源
It can't be taken away, right?
它帶不走對不對
the same situation
那同樣的情況
Therefore, it is very important to be able to integrate technology
所以能夠技術整合是一個很重要的
So we have to break through the past and say we fight alone
所以要突破過去說單打獨鬥的
In the past, if Taiwan went out alone, there would be no
過去台灣單打獨鬥的出去了就沒有
Now it's time to integrate the technology
現在要把它技術整合起來
not easy to lose
就不容易流失掉
And it will be sustainable in Taiwan
而且比較會在台灣可以持續發展
this is my personal opinion
這是我個人的看法
how does it look
看起來怎麼樣
this side in front
這邊前面
Okay, then there's that one
好 再後面是那個
Teacher Qiao Qiu
喬秋老師
ask the teacher
請問老師
to the one just mentioned
對剛才提到的那個
Ultra-masculine nothing too much interest
超雄性的無過於很有興趣
Then, since this is gray, adjust it naturally
那這個這個既然是灰自然調整
bred by the conditions
條件所培育出來
How to breed this little female bird
這個怎麼培育這種小女鳥
And that is to say, from a traditional biological point of view
還有就是說在傳統的生物學的觀點
That is to say, the performance-related body is not as good as X can be involved in the body.
就是說性能涉體比較沒有X能涉體的話
won't grow up or die
會長不大或死掉
How to overcome this problem
那這個是怎麼克服這個問題
In other words, this technology is in addition to no abalone
還有就是說這種技術是除了無鮑魚之外
Is there another one that can be used as well?
是不是還其他一種也可以施用
Thanks
謝謝
ok i'll go back to zai
好 我回到仔那裡
can you go back quickly
可不可以快速回去
That's the superhero line
就是那個超雄線
Yes yes X Y that one
對對 X Y 那一個
what about this
那這個呢
it this
它這個
Thanks
謝謝
This means that all male fish are used to mate here.
這個就是說這裡其實都是用雄性的魚去交配
The male fish thus becomes pseudo-maternal
那雄性的魚從而變成假性的母性
That means your XY fish is male, right?
就是說你XY的魚是雄的對不對
It can use this sex hormone, type X to feed it
它可以用此性激素、X型去餵食它
So it turns into a warm tide, not just a warm tide
所以它就暖潮會性現的花椅不是僅潮變成暖潮
So it's transgender, transgender fish
所以它是變性人、變性魚
So it's transgender, but it's an XY chromosome
所以它是變性的,但是它是XY染色體
But it's sexual, it can be soft, there's sperm on this side
但是它是此性的,它可以纏軟,這邊有精子
So after it was born, after it was bred
所以產下來以後,它配種下來以後
XY and XX are not half and half
XY跟XX不是一半一半
Only 25% of XX, 75% of male
XX只有25%,雄性的有75%
XY is still 50%, but YY is 1⁴
XY還是50%,但是YY的是1⁴
So this is hypermale, so males will be 75%
所以這個是超雄性,所以雄性會75%
So Chaoxiong uses it like this
所以超雄它是用這樣
In this way, I became this YY and cultivated it like this
這樣子變成這個YY這樣培養下來
but it only has one generation
但是它只有一代
That's why we have to return to the previous one every time.
就是所以每一次都要回歸到前面的這個一種
So this is just for breeding purposes
那麼所以這個只是為了養殖的目的
In turn, I just mentioned mullet roe
那反過來剛剛提到說烏魚子
Then you want pee, right?
那你就要牡牡對不對
So it is to make it turn bears into males
所以它就是要讓它都把熊的變成牡的
So the whole teeth are raised by males
那麼所以整齒都是牡牡在養
The tortoise is feeding the bear
那烏龜在養熊的
So this breeding
所以這養殖上面
In fact, these technologies in Taiwan were developed more than 20 years ago.
台灣這些技術其實二十幾年前都發展出來
Well it starts a bit like Try and error doing
那麼它開始有點像Try and error這樣做
Then slowly we will enter the import comparison
那麼慢慢我們就要進入導入比較
Biotechnology methods can identify
生科技的方法可以identify
Well wait these can be done
那麼等等這些可以來做
am i currently
目前我是不是
Good Mr. Qiu
好邱老師
Secretary-General Wu, thank you for your one-page research on Taiwan
吳秘書長謝謝你對台灣一頁的研究
communism in development
跟發展上的共產
Thank you for giving us this opportunity
謝謝你能夠提供給我們這個機會
Let's think about this question of fisheries development
來思考這個漁業發展方面的問題
i have two questions
我有兩個問題
The first is how do we define Taiwan eagle heels?
第一可是我們怎麼樣定義台灣雕跟
Wu Guoyu
吳國瑜
I think a lot of people want to know
我想這個很多人都想知道
Myself I just said Wu Guoyu
我自己我只是說吳國瑜
The second one is when we are studying
那第二個是在我們在研究
while doing scientific research
從事科學研究的時候
We also understand
同時我們也了解說
We are going to talk about the sustainable development of fishery resources
我們這個要談漁業資源的永續發展
can't leave the environment
不能離開環境
But I have been in the US for about ten years
可是我在美國大概那麼十多年
Then back to Taiwan I saw
然後回到台灣我看到
Because my family lives next to Zhuowei Creek
因為我家住在卓尉溪旁邊
Then I saw the whole side of Zhuowei Creek
然後我看到整個卓尉溪的旁邊
It turns out that the one that can be used for fish breeding
原來那個可以提供給魚類繁殖的
the tide environment
那個水潮的環境
has been replaced by that cement
已經被那個水泥取代了
Now many physique cases are made of cement
現在很多的體格案都是水泥
not only so
不只這樣
Then on the fine coast I want you to see
然後在細海岸我想各位看到
The so-called master of cement that is all cement
整個都是水泥的那個所謂的水泥的霸掌
something
什麼東西的
then we're going to talk about sustainable development
那我們要談永續發展
we can't leave the environment
我們就不能離開環境
So what I'm wondering now is that
所以我現在想知道就是說
How can we change this
我們怎麼樣能夠改變這種
the trend of this development
這種發展的趨勢
Let the reproduction of this fish be able to
讓這個魚類的繁殖能夠
fog as much as possible
盡量揮霧到
Chicken wings can't be completely fogged
雞翅不能完全揮霧
i wish to say
我希望說
able to keep some
能夠保持一些
Relatively surplus fish breeding
比較適餘的魚類繁殖
like a rainy-breeding environment
像漫雨繁殖的環境這樣
we can talk about sustainability
我們才能夠談永續
Otherwise we can only say
要不然我們只能說
From the environment has been pushed down to the laboratory
從環境一直推縮到實驗室來
In this way, I am actually the reverse
那這樣我其實是逆向的
We should develop outside
我們應該往外發展才對
So I'm here to listen to you today
所以我今天特別來聽你講
that's why i want to know
就是目的我想要知道
That is how we can improve the environment
就是說我們怎麼樣來改善這個環境
before being able to
然後才能夠
To maintain a more sustainable development
保持越致遠的永續發展
Thanks
謝謝
i think this is a big issue
我想這個是很重大問題
Our land and resources in Taiwan
我們台灣國土資源的
this childcare issue
這個保育的問題
The first question is more scientific
第一個問題比較科學的問題
business issues
跟商業的問題
What is a Taiwanese sculpture
台灣雕是什麼
because we all convey
因為我們大家傳達
i think abalone is a cheap fish
我認為烏鮑魚是很便宜的魚
But the black abalone has a characteristic
但是烏鮑魚有一個特性
Abalone can adapt to fresh water
烏鮑魚可以適應淡水
Can also adapt to sea water
也可以適應海水
you know
你知道
So Taiwan especially has red black abalone
所以台灣尤其有紅色的烏鮑魚
After pre-planting
預種出來以後
before they bring the fish to market
他們把魚到可以上市之前
They slowly transform it
他們慢慢給它轉化
form in seawater
形化在海水裡面
So it forms in the sea water
所以它形化在海水裡面
it has added value to the product
它有增加產品的價值
Not only is red turned into a vulture
不但紅色變成像雕類
Eagles are expensive fish
雕類是高價的魚
The second very important thing is
第二個很重要的就是
it's in the sea
它在海水裡面
it will remove all kinds of earthy taste
它會去掉各種土味
To get rid of organic pests
去排除掉機生蟲
The third
第三個
fourth fish
第四個魚肉
it will become stronger
它會變得比較結實
because it will reach the sea in pursuit
因為它會抵海追尋
So then what do we do carving
所以後來我們做什麼雕類
You can make Sasimi
你看可以做Sasimi
Why Ubalone Can Be Sasimi
為什麼烏鮑魚可以做Sasimi
Because it has been transformed by sea water
因為它有經過海水的情化
so
所以
The head of the family said that this is called Taiwan sculpture
當家就是說這個叫台灣雕
Let everyone change their image and become this advanced
讓大家形象一改就變成這個高級
so we get to this
所以我們到這個
Especially this restaurant that speaks by mouth
尤其是口裡講話的這個餐廳
Its business film must have Taiwanese carvings, right?
它的生意片一定有台灣雕對不對
There are also supermarkets
超市也都有賣
So where is the Taiwanese sculpture?
所以台灣雕哪裡有這個
This is a product specially developed in Taiwan
這是台灣特別發展出來的一個商品
basically it's a hybrid
基本上它是一個雜交種
This is the Oreos Mozambica
就是這個Oreos Mozambica
Not Oreos Nelotica and Oreos
不是Oreos Nelotica跟Oreos
Oreochromis
Oreochromis
Oreos and Nelotica are hybrids
Oreos跟Nelotica是雜交的
Then the purpose of its hybridization is to produce the offspring of this all-bear
那麼它雜交的目的是要產生這個全熊的後代
so it's not treated with hormones
所以它不用荷爾蒙處理
it is hybridized
它是用雜交
Second your question is very good
第二個你的問題是非常好
That is to say, the river bank and coast of Taiwan
就是說台灣的這個河岸跟海岸
So for this some protection proposals
那麼為了這個一些保護提案
Huang Hong and so on are forced by Ba Zhang's phone call.
黃紅等等就是霸掌的電話還逼
The proposal is to combine and assemble
那提案就是合體就組起來
Well, I think if the Taiwan government is determined
那麼我覺得台灣政府有決心的話
The first one is to restore the ecological engineering method
第一個要恢復生態工法
That is to say, your verification case is to
也就是說你的核案是要
There is no way to fully return to nature
沒有辦法完全恢復到自然
It is a quasi-ecological environment to be exposed
它是類生態的環境要受到出來
That is to say, no hard cement blocks
也就是說不要硬幫幫的水泥塊
this way to do this
這樣提往這樣做
step by step i saw
是要逐步的我看過
Maybe Mr. Qiu is from Neia
可能邱老師是內亞的
I can't talk nonsense
我這個不能亂講
For example, using stones of different sizes
那比如說用大小的不同的石塊
Then it is similar to returning to the state of the river
那麼類似恢復到河川的這個狀態
so let it suck
所以讓它吸流的狀態
Let these original aquatic organisms fish and shrimp be classed
讓這些原來水生生物魚蝦被類
It has four environments that allow it to survive
它有四個環境可以讓它可以活存
Then this environment is subject to
那麼這環境就受到
The second most important thing is not to pollute
第二個最重要是不能污染
man-made pollution factory pollution
人為的污染 工廠的污染
Pollution of this household etc.
這個家庭的污染等等
this can't come in
這個不能進來
I think these two can do
我想這兩項能夠做得到
Of course the third item is the pollution of alpine farmland
那當然第三項是高山農田的污染
Fertilizer Pesticides wash down
肥料 農藥 沖刷下來
If these can be prevented
那這些如果可以防止的話
Taiwan can recover really is
台灣是可以恢復真的是
I see Taiwan is beautiful
看見台灣那個很美
To see beautiful Taiwan, no
要看到漂亮的台灣 不是
Taiwan that has been devastated by this
受到這個破壞的台灣
I think this question is very important
我覺得這個問題是非常重要的問題
In this way, our biological resources can be sustainable
那這樣的話我們的生物資源就可以永續可以來
this development
這個發展
Thank you
謝謝你
ok come here
好 來這邊
ask the secretary general
請教秘書長
The genetic modification of the fish just mentioned
剛剛提到的那個魚類的基因轉值
that technology
那的技術
Is this similar to the genetic modification of soybeans
這是否類似那個黃豆的基因改造
In the same industry, we actually talk about genetic modification
同業的其實我們講說基因的改造
I often have to speak the real meaning from the original English
我常常要講真正從原來英文的意思
You know that an organism has about 25,000 to 30,000 genes before
你知道一個生物的基因大概有25000個到30000個基因之前
In fact, when we talk about transformation, it is as if you said four years a day
其實我們講改造是好像你說一天四年
Huang Zi wants to reform, what is reform?
黃子要改造 什麼叫改造
Maybe keep the basics and replace all the others to be remodeled, right?
可能基礎留著其他全部給換掉要改造對不對
In fact, in this translated noun
其實在這個翻譯的名詞
I think the first one is that there is a considerable gap
我覺得第一個就是有相當大的落差
We call GMO in English is Genetically Modified Organism
我們英文叫GMO就是Generically Modified Organism
It is based on genetically modified organisms
它是基於遺傳修飾的生物
It seems that the eyebrows are too thin
修飾好像是眉毛太細了
I want to draw thicker, right?
我要畫粗一點對不對
It's okay to talk about modification, right?
這個講修飾是可以對不對
this micro
這個微
But our transformation
但是我們這種改造
Remodeling is like a revolution, I will replace them all for you
改造好像革命一樣就全部給你換掉
actually this
其實是這個
Caused the public in our society to this
造成我們這個社會大眾對這個
The knowledge of this technology
這一個科技的認知
It actually deviates quite a bit
它其實偏差是蠻大的
The first and the second means
第一個 第二個就是說
We import the genes of foreign aid
我們導入外援的基因
go inside a creature
到一個生物裡面去
It's all GMO
都算是GMO
Na GMO
那GMO
The history of our human development has existed
我們人類發展歷史本來就存在
Human beings have been farming since the beginning
人類自從有農業的活動開始
For example, your kind is genetically modified.
比如說你一種就是基因改造
That transformation is better than ours
那改造比我們這個
with this particular gene
用這個特定的基因的
change to a greater extent
改變的程度更大
degree of self-exchange because of a
自換的程度 因為一種
right
對不對
so we
所以我們
If it is to return to us
如果是要回歸到我們
8,000 years ago to 10,000 years ago
八千年前到一萬年前
our ancestors
我們的老祖宗
You said I ate all the wild ones
你說我都完全吃野生的
That's fine
That's fine
is you to wild to
就是你到野生到
or wild
或野生
back to the times
就回歸到時代
So our concept
所以我們的觀念
even scientific
就算科學的
i often say
我常常講說
When discussing or recognizing GMOs
討論或是認知GMO的時候
have science
要有科學
based discussion
為依據的討論
Only then can there be a way to truly understand GMOs
才有辦法說真正了解GMO
In particular, I am talking about this life safety assessment
我特別講到這個生萬全評估
that's very strict
那是非常嚴謹的
Then this piece is linked to this
那麼這一塊連動到這個
Why does the Council of Agriculture in Taiwan say
我們台灣為什麼農委會指準說
Watch this GMO that is all medicine
觀賞都是醫藥的這個GMO
it allows us to do
它是讓我們可以去做
So why did we come to this viewing instrument
所以為什麼我們會走到這個觀賞儀
We put this technology
我們把這個技術
build a theory like this
把這樣子的理論把它建構起來
But just mentioned that the human population has increased so much
但是剛剛提到人類的人口這麼增加
right
對不對
We in Taiwan don't seem to feel it
我們台灣好像是沒有感受到
food pressure
糧食的壓力
but in the world
但是世界上
20% of the world's population is still
現在還有差不多20%的世界的人口
it is on the verge of activation
它是在激活邊緣
Then the supply of these foods in the future
那將來這些糧食的提供
I personally feel
我個人覺得
Humans still have technological development
人類還是有科技的發展
follow human development
跟著人類的發展
It seems that it goes along with the development
好像明明之中它配著發展
When the human population is 9 billion
當人類的人口90億的時候
i don't believe that
我就不相信說
What we eat every day is not GMO
我們每天吃的都不是 GMO
Because this feeds nine billion people
因為這個要餵養九十億人口
Thirty-seven years later Thirty-six years later
三十七年後 三十六年後而已
So this is the time to start a rational discussion
所以這個是目前就要開始要理性討論
have scientific knowledge
有科學認知
I personally do it from the point of view
我是個人是從這樣的觀點來做
do this
來做這樣
Sometimes our government departments will consider saying
有時候我們的政府部門會考慮到說
This will affect our export
這會影響到我們的外銷
For example, GM's papaya is actually the world's leading technology
比如說 GM的木瓜其實技術是世界領先
But the Agricultural Committee is not the only one
但是農委就不只他
He said you planted a bad
他說你種了糟糕
Foreign countries say I will not buy your papaya from Taiwan
外國說我不買你台灣的木瓜
I think you use a specific coin to grow this papaya
我覺得你用特定的工幣的地方去種這個木瓜
You are the guarantee that none of this is leaked
你就是 guarantee 這些都不外流
It was required by law
本來法規上就這樣要求
you can't assume say
你不能 assume 說
because when you planted
因為你種了的時候
export can't
外銷就不能夠
People Think You Might Have GMOs
人家認為你可能有 GMO
inside
在裡面
How does this look like getting certified
這個是怎麼樣子取得認證
This letter of acquisition of citizenship
取得國籍的這個信
I think this government needs to work on it
我想這個政府要用點功夫
Here are some of my personal advances
這是我個人的一些前進
okay, is there anything else
好 還有沒有什麼樣的
can ask a question
可以請教一個問題
yes come please
是 來 請
i want to ask
我想請問一下
That is, the types of fish you just mentioned
就是說您剛才提的那幾種魚類
all belong to that is to say
都比較屬於就是說
local small fish
local的小型魚類
Is that because of it
那是不是因為它這個
But the love of the whole ocean
但是整個海洋的深戀
it has some large return fish
它有一些大型的回油魚類
like you mentioned
像您剛才提到
The tuna factory where Musko and the others make it
穆斯哥他們做的鮪魚的那個廠
that's like this
那類似這種
that is why
就是說為什麼
this biotechnology
這種生物技術
Is it possible to do the same
是不是也可以同樣
used in the kind of large return oil fish
用在那種大型的回油魚類
Then if from a
那如果從一個
Research unit's point of view
研究單位的觀點
why only do
為什麼只做
That is to say, do not do the above
就是說下面的 不做上面
OK, what he's talking about is that
OK 他講的問題就是說
This is the top
這個要頂層的
upper fish
上層的魚類
like tuna fin fish
像鮪魚 鰭魚
these this
這些 這個
Costs involving the environment, technology, and investment
牽涉到環境、技術、投資的成本
Why tuna?
為什麼鮪魚呢?
because tuna is in
因為鮪魚在
What they raise is mainly exported to the market in Tokyo, Japan
他們養的主要是外銷到日本東京族地的市場去
Although tuna can be successfully bred in captivity
鮪魚現在雖然有人工繁殖可以成功
But the amount is still not enough
但是量還是不夠多
so their tuna is
所以他們鮪魚是
Mexico or Australia
墨西哥那邊或是澳洲那邊
they have that
他們有那個
Fishing boat, Tuna boat
魚船、鮪魚網船
arrive
到
school of tuna
鮪魚群
this little school of fish
這個小魚群
We are talking about little fish
我們講小魚是已經
This 35kg tuna
這個35公斤的鮪魚
tuna grow big
鮪魚要長很大
they are tuna nets
他們是鮪魚網
Then
然後
after tuna net
鮪魚網以後
after shrinking
縮起來以後
put in
放到
In this Xiangwang
這個湘網裡面
The Xiangwang in the sea is very active because of the tuna
那海上的湘網因為鮪魚的活動力非常強
very big
體型又非常大
So the tuna from Xiangwang
所以那鮪魚的湘網的
this diameter
這個直徑
must be more than 50 meters
都要50公尺以上
so this
所以這個
Taiwan because
台灣因為
There are so many in Taiwan, you must be in a place without Taiwan’s waves
台灣多啊 你一定要在一個沒有台灣海浪
Only when the impact is too large can there be a solution
衝擊太大地方才有辦法
So they pass through this way
所以他們透過這樣子
should allow him enough room to return oil
應該讓他足夠的回油的空間
To be able to raise a fish like this tuna
才能夠養這個鮪魚這樣子的魚
Then the rest is no way this captive breeding
那其餘是沒有辦法這個人工養殖
Then Taiwan was not what it used to be, and now it still exists
那台灣曾經不是曾經的 現在還有
We are raising sea sharks
我們是養海鮫啦
Sea shark in Penghu in Xiaoliuqiu
海鮫在澎湖 在小琉球
There are industry players who cooperate with the Water City Office
都有業者跟水市所這邊合作
In fact, it was very successful
其實養得非常成功
But here comes the problem, that is, there are two reasons
但是問題來了 就是說有兩個原因
One is a typhoon, it may die and be easily damaged
一個是颱風 可能會相亡容易破損
the second is
第二個就是
some he wants to protect his fish from being stolen
有一些他為了保護他魚不被偷
Some people in Taiwan say that night is the king of tuna
台灣有人說晚上是偷鮪魚王
where does he go to make water
他要造水才去哪裡
He said I was caught at sea
他說我是海上撈的
A businessman in Taiwan said this
一業者台灣的這個就說
how to say this this
怎麼講 這個這個
There's no way this security can do a good job
這個保全沒有辦法做得很好
So now raise Hailey
所以現在養海利呢
It's only in Penghu, maybe Mintong is relatively simple there.
只在澎湖還可能那邊民通比較純樸吧
There is no such transparent clothing in the sea
沒有這個海上的這個透衣
The Clothes Festival is coming, although there is still
透衣節來透 雖然還有
But Xiao Liuqiu has almost shrunk
但是小琉球幾乎已經是縮起來
that's a pity
那蠻可惜的
because haley
因為海利呢
It can grow up to ten kilograms
它就可以養到十幾公斤
Moreover, some politicians can export Japanese
而且呢 有的政客可以外銷日本的
There are still, but the quantity is no longer
現在還有 但是量已經不是
then as popular as five or six years ago
那麼像五六年前那樣盛行
we used to say
我們曾經就是說
The Council of Agriculture also hopes to raise Haili from Taiwan
農委會也希望就是養台灣的海利
Like this, this Norwegian salmon
就像這個這個挪威養鮭魚這樣子
Become a fish species representing Taiwan
變成代表台灣的一個魚種
Then it slowly evolved into raising grouper
那後來慢慢演變就變成養石斑魚了
So now take the grouper as the
所以現在以石斑這個為
our main this this
我們主要的這個這個
a sign is
一個招牌 是
But recently the problem is like this
但是最近是問題這樣子
Xi Jinping slapped his tongue after coming up
習近平上來以後打舌
So originally Spani was expensive in mainland China
所以本來史班尼在大陸是高價的
You can't treat guests with Spenny now
現在請客不能夠用史班尼請客
The harmful immigrants not only breed
那害致的移民不但養殖的
Our Spani is live fish transport
我們的史班尼是活魚運輸
is a live fish that is operated by a boat
是用船運作活的魚
Shipping to Tianjin, Qingdao, Shanghai
運到天津、青島、上海
Previously only created Hong Kong
以前只創了香港
Now it is a few ports out of the way
現在是它偏不幾個港口出去
But our price is underground
但是我們的價格在地下
So you are very lucky
所以各位其實滿有福氣
Spanney is much cheaper now
現在的史班尼便宜很多
I asked a few days ago
我前幾天問了一下
like a normal shift
像一般的清班
The side price of one kilogram is only 180 yuan
一公斤持邊價180塊而已
More than 300 yuan before
以前300多塊
it dropped the general price
它跌了一般價錢
so encourage everyone
所以鼓勵大家
It's all us Taiwan Spenny
都是我們台灣史班尼
Our immigrants will not learn without loss
我們的移民才不會學本無虧
Are there any other questions?
還有沒有其他的問題
I want to ask Secretary-General Wu
要請教吳秘書長
Thank you Secretary-General Wu for giving us a wonderful speech
謝謝吳秘書長給我們很精彩的演講
let's applaud and thank him
讓我們鼓掌再謝謝他
thank you all thank you
謝謝大家 謝謝